<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvvere to a popish libell intituled A petition to the bishops, preachers, and gospellers, lately spread abroad in the north partes. By Francis Bunny Prebendary of Durham; sometimes fellow of Magdalen Colledge in Oxford</title>
            <author>Bunny, Francis, 1543-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106918</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842625</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842625</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7293</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17245)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7293)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1196:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvvere to a popish libell intituled A petition to the bishops, preachers, and gospellers, lately spread abroad in the north partes. By Francis Bunny Prebendary of Durham; sometimes fellow of Magdalen Colledge in Oxford</title>
                  <author>Bunny, Francis, 1543-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 159, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With the text of the petition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Petition to the bishops, preachers, and gospellers</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7293:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7293:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVERE TO A POPISH LIBELL IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>A Petition to the Biſhops, Preachers, and Gospellers,</hi> lately ſpread abroad in the North partes, By FRANCIS BVNNY <hi>Prebenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Durham; ſometimes fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of Magdalen Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Thus ſaith the Lord: ſtande in the waies and beholde and aske for the old waies, which is the good way, and walke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and yee ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules. <bibl>
                  <hi>Ierem. 6.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Joſeph Barnes, Printer <hi>to the Vniverſity.</hi> 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7293:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7293:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO ALL POPISH</hi> RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants who deſire to know the truth, <hi>F.B.</hi> wiſheth grace to ſee and to be ſorry for their ignorance &amp; errour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> complayneth grievouſly of ſome, whoſe <hi>wordes were ſofter then butter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.22.</note> 
               <hi>yet vvarr vvas in their harte: they vvere more gentle then oile, yet they were ſwords.</hi> Wherein he ſeemeth to me, to paint out in ſome liuely colours, the Recuſants of our daies who hauing bloud in their minds, &amp; moſt ſavage purpoſes ſtill in hammering: yet to blinde mens eies, or to turne away their harts from anie care of preuenting
<pb facs="tcp:7293:3"/> their danger, deale by <hi>Petition</hi> &amp; <hi>Requeſt,</hi> as if they were verie loiall and reaſonable ſubiects. To this end (by that which hath followed we maie iudge) was that <hi>Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in <hi>September</hi> laſt ſent abroad, <hi>To the Biſhops, Preachers, and Goſpellers,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceiued by their wordes of charitie, we ſhould not once doubt of anie vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable purpoſe that they would haue, &amp; ſo ſhoulde bee taken in the ſnares which they had privilie laide. But how ſo euer they ſmoothlie dawbed ouer their moſt monſtrous deſignes, and couered with ſhew of ſugred words their moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous intent: yet the event hath ſhewed, that vnder the wings of that <hi>Popiſh</hi> diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, was hatched the moſt ſtrange and vnnaturall treaſon, that hart of man could thinke of; in reſpect whereof, the <hi>maſſacre</hi> of <hi>Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> though inhumane, the purpoſe of <hi>Haman</hi> though very cruel, the murder committed by <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> of the <hi>Shechemits,</hi> though exceeding bloudie; yea the Attempt of <hi>Pope Lucius</hi> the 2. though monſtrous enough, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb facs="tcp:7293:3"/> neereſt to this of our <hi>Recuſants,</hi> yet haue ſome honeſt coulour of excuſe. For in that of <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> being ſeduced by bad <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell,</hi> was made to beleeue that by no other means he could execute Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice (as they tearmed it) on his <hi>ſubiects,</hi> &amp; therin not many of great reckoning di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Haman</hi> ſought the deſtruction of ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; The childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Iacob</hi> had their <hi>ſiſter</hi> abuſed by <hi>Hamours</hi> ſonne who was <hi>Lorde</hi> of that Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie; &amp; the attempt of <hi>Lucius</hi> againſt the <hi>Praetor</hi> and all the <hi>Senators</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> was by open force, and not by ſuch daſtardlie or cowardlie practiſes. But this <hi>Popiſh</hi> deſigne, was to the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of almoſt al the <hi>noble, learned</hi> either in <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie or Law, wiſe</hi> and <hi>worſhipfull</hi> in the Land, onlie to attaine to their owne wicked deſires without cauſe of iuſt wrath not of <hi>forainers,</hi> but of Contriemen and kinſfolke, and that in a moſt treacherous and ſudden manner. It ſhal not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hencforth be ſtrange to me, that our <hi>Learned Antiquarie</hi> writeth of certaine ſprings with vs,<note place="margin">Camden in Brit.</note> that turne wood into
<pb facs="tcp:7293:4"/> ſtone: neither yet that of <hi>Circe</hi> fabled to change men into ſwine: ſince that wee ſee the <hi>Popiſh</hi> humour, maketh the harts of men to be harder then flint: and <hi>Romiſh Circes</hi> by their inchantments, can cauſe them who before had humane &amp; pitifull affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s like others to neighbours, frinds prince, and countrie, to caſt of al naturall loue or dutie to all, hauing harts more harde then ſtones, and being in crueltie worſe then <hi>Tigers.</hi> Oh S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. wil ſome men ſaie, not al Papiſts were acquainted with this conſpiracie. I am of that minde too. But withal this is my reſolution, that all perfect Papiſts, &amp; ſuch as are reconciled to the Pope, though they knewe not of it yet being called vpon, would haue beene aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts therin. For that ſubiecting of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to the <hi>Pope,</hi> as their Head &amp; direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, and vowing their obedience to his commandements, which if he ſaie they be to the furtherance of the <hi>Catholick</hi> faith, they dare not but execute them if they be able; maketh vs iuſtlie to doubt of their faith &amp; loialtie to our <hi>dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7293:4"/> And if all knew not the verie myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie of this Iniquitie, and the depth of of this purpoſe, namelie in what ſort, or at what houre it was intended to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted: yet in the <hi>North parts,</hi> where this <hi>Petition</hi> perchance was framed; yea and in other places too, as I haue beene crediblie informed, there was ſuch bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and contempt of law, ſo litle feare to offend, and ſuch open reſort to their <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous</hi> ſeruice: that manie good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudge nether are deceiued (J ſuppoſe) therin, that moſt of the <hi>Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</hi> had at the leaſt ſome great expectation, of an <hi>Alteration</hi> of the <hi>Eſtate.</hi> Nether is it much to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded that the <hi>Preiſts</hi> tell vs, that in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill matters, and if the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wealth of our <hi>Countrie,</hi> they would not obay; as <hi>VVatſons Treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> him ſelfe being a <hi>Preist,</hi> and a <hi>Teacher</hi> of that leſſon, did proue vnto vs. For I am ſure he could not make it a matter of <hi>Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> (except of <hi>Popiſh Religion</hi>) to murder his prince, to whom hee owed all ſubiection. And who knoweth not, that it is an eaſie
<pb facs="tcp:7293:5"/> matter for the <hi>Pope,</hi> whoſe voice <hi>Papiſtes</hi> take as the voice of God, to make his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorites to beleeue, that all things tend to <hi>Religion,</hi> that will inlarge his Authoritie? And what will hee not commende as a thing Religious, that compared the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of <hi>Henry the</hi> 3. the French King, to that Miraculous worke of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>Incarnation</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection?</hi> Can we i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that they who dare vtter ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable blaſphemies, wil ſhame to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme anie thing? And theſe ſo dangerous ſubiects, becauſe their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences wil not ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to come to our Churches, muſt craue ether to be reſolued that it is lawful to come to our <hi>ſeruice</hi> (which they are ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t neuer to be, for they wil nether hear vs, nor read our writings) or elſe be freed from ſuch puniſhments as <hi>Lawes</hi> impoſe vpon <hi>Recuſants.</hi> A ſtrang conſcience it is that manie of them haue, who would bee thought to be more ſingular, and to haue more feeling and feare to offend then the common ſort, &amp; yet if we trie their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, they are not to be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="tcp:7293:5"/> the beſt ſort of ſuch as follow noe other direction for Religion, then to bee obedient vnto his Maieſties Lawes, with out reſpect vnto that God commandeth. Not to ſpeake of their vſual whoredoms, oppreſſions, malice towards others, and ſuch like good qualities which dailie are ſeene and knowne to be among them: let the <hi>fift of November</hi> bee a witneſſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt that daie ſhall be numbred in the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenders,</hi> of the more then Turkiſh cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Poperie.</hi> Haue they a conſcience to ſteale, to liue in adulterie, to deale hardlie with their Tenants or neighbors againſt Gods laws: &amp; wil not their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to <hi>heare</hi> that <hi>Service</hi> wherein themſelues confeſſe there is no evill? Stand not anie more vpon ſuch tearmes O yee ſeduced <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Leaue that <hi>Romiſh Synagogue</hi> whoſe doctrine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the worſhip of God, is ſuperſtitious and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> whoſe deuotion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in toies and trifles, &amp; <hi>bodily exerciſe that profiteth little.</hi> Leaue I ſay that crue that warranteth, nay maketh <hi>meritorious</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:7293:6"/> honorable the depoſing or killing of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> and <hi>Pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tates.</hi> Depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that <hi>church</hi> whereof to bee is but diſcredit; For the chiefe <hi>Teachers</hi> of <hi>Poperie</hi> aſſure vs, that to bee of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> there nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no <hi>Internall vertue,</hi> but onlie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that faith that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> teach, &amp; to acknowledge the <hi>Pope</hi> to be ſupreame head. The <hi>Divell</hi> himſelfe may be of that Church: what credit gaine you by being of that companie? Be aſhamed of them that teach you neither to keepe <hi>oath</hi> nor <hi>promiſe,</hi> to ſuch as they call <hi>heretickes.</hi> To be ſhort, ſeeing that <hi>church,</hi> hath ſo put vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her the face of a harlot, that ſhe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to be accompted, in corrupting Scriptures, &amp; the writings of the fathers moſt ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turous, in treacheries moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, in crueltie moſt barbarous, &amp; in all odious &amp; vnnatural atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts, moſt audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.4.</note> 
               <hi>Go out of her, that you be not partakers of her ſinnes, &amp; that yee receiue not of her plagues. O Romiſh Recuſants</hi> (for <hi>Catholiks</hi> I maie not call you, it is not a name that you maie truelie claime) <hi>you haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:7293:6"/> your first loue,</hi> or at the leaſt that loue,<note place="margin">Apoc. 2.4.</note> that you ſeemd once to bear to the <hi>truth: Remember from whence you are fallen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. Eſa. 51.1.</note> 
               <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and doe your firſt works.</hi> And as <hi>Eſay</hi> the <hi>Prophet</hi> calleth the <hi>Iewes</hi> to conſider of <hi>Abraham</hi> in whom they were firſt cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to be Gods Peculiar people: ſo doe I moſt earneſtlie intreate you,<note place="margin">Philip. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>If there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſolation in Chriſt, if anie comfort of loue, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if anie compaſsion and mercie,</hi> euen of your own ſoules, that you looke not from hence forth vnto the glittering ſhewe of exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall pride in a Mortall man;<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>but vnto Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the authour and finiſher of our faith.</hi> Marke well what he in his word comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that you maie doe it, what worſhip he requireth that you may yeeld it, what duties he teacheth that you maie learne and obey the ſame. So ſhall you finde the righte true waies to your feete, and peace vnto your ſoules:<note place="margin">Eſa. 50.11.</note> whereas if you ſtill walke in <hi>the ſparkes of the fire vvhich you haue kindled</hi> (to your ſelues) <hi>This ſhall you haue at Gods hand, you ſhal lie downe in ſorrow.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7293:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7293:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7293:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7293:8"/>
            <head>An Anſwere to a Popiſh Petition.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Doniah the ſonne of David by Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gith,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 3.4.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaw he could not by might &amp; violence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to bee king (though he attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it,<note place="margin">1. King. 1.5.</note> David yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,) ſought by ſubtilty to attaine ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, in cauſing Bethſabe the mother of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lomon,<note place="margin">1. King. 2.17.</note> (David being now dead) to ſue to her ſonne, that hee might haue Abiſhag the Sunamite to wife. The Romiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks (for ſo they wil be termed,) haue ſought by many violent meanes, &amp; thoſe moſt barbarous and cruell to beare the ſway in this Church &amp; Common-wealth, but God not giving ſucceſſe anſwerable to their deſires, but fruſtrating their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wicked hopes, they proue whether by falſe flattery they can deceiue, ſince by violence and might they can do nothing. To this ende haue they preſented their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7293:9"/> ſupplications, both to our late gracious Governeſſe &amp; Queene of everliving me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, &amp; alſo ſince to our moſt dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne, that ſince by murder and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe they cannot performe their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, they may make triall, if by his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces good leaue, (in graunting them their deſired Toleration) they may ſubiect this noble Realme, to the Vicar of Rome.</p>
            <p>Diverſe petitions haue to this end bin ſcattered abroad, ſome alſo delivered to his Maieſties hands; but God hitherto hath mercifully preſerved him, ſo that he hath not ſuffered himſelfe to bee taken in thoſe their ſnares, neither over-reached by their crafty inchantments. But now of late haue they framed another petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, more reaſonable then their former ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications haue beene, both in reſpect of the manner, more milde &amp; in ſhew more humble; and in regard of the matter too, becauſe it requireth not a Toleration of Poperie, or immunitie from penalties by law impoſed, as the reſt of them (that I haue ſeene) doe, ſimply and without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7293:9"/> but the drift thereof is (as by the words I can gather) at the leaſt to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, that if good reaſons may be ſhewed, how they of the Romiſh Religion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger of deadly ſinne may reſort to our Churches, they would be moſt ready ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>More reaſonable, I ſay, it is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others, which may rather be called comminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then ſupplications: in this yet an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable demand, that the thing ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſo throughly performed, by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry learned treatiſes, is yet now againe required at our hands, and that with ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence, as that the Petitioner ſeemeth to aſſure himſelfe, that his deſire herein cannot be ſatiſfied. And in truth I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his minde too; not becauſe the thing he requireth, is hard in it ſelfe to be done; but becauſe their hearts are for the moſt part ſo hardened againſt the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble truth of Gods vndoubted worde, that that ſeed can hardly take any roote with them.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore this petition is in a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7293:10"/> manner a challenge to provoke vs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter him, and carieth perchance a great ſhew among his favorits, that wrot it, as if the cauſe muſt needs be good, that hath ſo confident a patron or proctour to defend the ſame: I thinke it not amiſſe to examine the ſame as briefly as I can, and to buckle my ſelfe to anſwere by Gods grace the prowd brag of this Popiſh Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah. Who though he raile not ſo plainely as did that Philiſtine, vpon the hoſt of the living God; yet covertly hee promiſeth himſelfe the victorie, &amp; by his overbold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of words, hopeth to aſſure his friends that al is on his ſide cocke ſure, and no pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill at al.</p>
            <p>And having conſidered with my ſelfe of the ſumme of this Petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I finde <hi>three</hi> general points thereof, vnto ſome one whereof, al that is ſaid may be referred. For <hi>firſt</hi> there is a complaint of the hard caſe the Recuſants are in. <hi>Then</hi> followeth a narration or reporte of the meanes by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſed, to redreſſe the ſame. <hi>In the third</hi> place commeth the ſuit it ſelfe or petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7293:10"/> with ſome ſhew of reaſon to perſwade &amp; moue the reader. And though my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is to handle every of theſe parts: yet ſo, as that I will followe the very trace of his words.<note place="margin">1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Pars.</hi>
               </note> Thus therfore his petition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth, and with this inſcription.</p>
            <q>A Petition to the Biſhops, Preachers, and Goſpellers.</q>
            <p>That he maketh petition vnto Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops anb preachers concerning inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, were not to be miſliked, becauſe it is intended that ſuch men both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their learning are beſt able, and for their place and office, ſhould be moſt ready and willing to performe ſuch due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But that ſo many ſufficient ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this demande, ſeeme to him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, ſheweth that the <hi>Petitioner</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not read that is written, or read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it with a preiudicate opinion, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he hath a purpoſe not to be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied: but that he rather aſketh queſtions of our Biſhops &amp; preachers, as the Scribs and Phariſes did of Chriſt often, not to informe themſelues, but to intrap him in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7293:11"/> his words, or to trie if poſſibly they might haue put him to ſilence.</p>
            <p>And as touching the <hi>Goſpellers</hi> here ſpoken of, if by that tearme he meane the profeſſours of that Religion which the ſaid preachers teach, (as J ſuppoſe he doth) I am then glad that he imagineth there ſhould in our <hi>Lay</hi> people ſuch abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of knowledg be found, that they as well as others, ſhould be required to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie, the learned <hi>diuines</hi> among the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi> in points of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For it is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they ſhould denie that to their owne Layitie, that they require in ours: &amp; then ſhal they not from henceforth hang alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at the lippes of ignorant <hi>Prieſts</hi> their blind guides, but ſhalbe better able to inſtruct and informe themſelues.</p>
            <p>Nether wil I iudge that this petitioner vſeth this name <hi>Goſpeller,</hi> in Ironicall ſcorne &amp; mockerie, as ſome other of that Sect doe.<note place="margin">Tabui. <hi>3.</hi> vi. gene. haereſ.</note> So doth Lindanus that ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful companion, both againſt the Goſpel it ſelfe, ſpeaking of ſome who ſaith he, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt certaine things, <hi>haud ſecùs, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> à pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7293:11"/> Lutheraniſmo (Euangelio dico) alieniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima: as if they were quite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to pure Lutheraniſme (I meane the Goſpell:)</hi> and alſo againſt the profeſſours therof:<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trophe lectoris catholici ad Euangelicos iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos: An Apoſtrophe of the catholick rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to theſe goſpellers</hi> with ſuch a like ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit doth prophane Eckius cal ſuch,<note place="margin">Enchirid. de ſcript.</note> 
               <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologos atramentales, Inky diuines.</hi> Nether is the blaſphemy of Capreolus here to be omitted,<note place="margin">Capreol. l. <hi>5.</hi> Elench. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. <hi>Act. 24.5. &amp; 14.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hoſ. lin. <hi>1.</hi> de haereſ.</note> who (as Tertullus dealt with S. Paul, branding him with the name of heretick for embracing and teaching this ſelfeſame Goſpel) reckoneth among his Heretickes <hi>Evangelicos Goſpellers,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him alſo did Hoſius, and as he alſo citeth <hi>Lindanus</hi> in his <hi>dubita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio,</hi> dialog. 2</p>
            <p>But howſoeuer theſe Enemies to the Goſpel of Chriſt &amp; his vndoubted word, ſpeake or write, reprochfully or blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly of that <hi>glorious Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yet as <hi>wee are not aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt: for it is the power of God vnto ſaluation to euery on that beleeueth:</hi> ſo doe we not deny the name, or take in evil part to be called
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7293:12"/> 
               <hi>Goſpellers,</hi> ſince that we knowe it to be the inſtrument of our regeneration: <hi>For in Chriſt Ieſus</hi> (faith S. Paul to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians) <hi>I haue begotten you through the Goſpel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.15.</note> And the ſame Apoſtle teſtifieth to the Theſſalonians,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.13.14. 2. Cor. 6.7. Iacob. 1.18. 2. Cor. 5.18 19. Phil. 2.16.</note> that <hi>God hath called them to the faith of truth, by the Goſpell.</hi> Therfore is it called the <hi>word of truth</hi> by S. Paul and by S. Iames too: as alſo, <hi>the word or miniſtery of reconciliation;</hi> &amp; <hi>the word of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nether deny we but that we may more iuſtly make claime to that title, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the Papiſts in the world ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do: for that our preaching and doctrine is according to that Goſpel, wheras the teachers in the Romiſh Synagogue, <hi>worſhip God in vaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15.9.</note> 
               <hi>teaching for doctrines mans pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,</hi> and inſteed of the ſound and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome food of gods vndoubted word, they feed them that follow them, with empty huſkes of mens traditions. Howſoever therfore our aduerſaries meane whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cal vs by that na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, yet we haue iuſt cauſe to reioice therin. becauſe therby we are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7293:12"/> aſſured, that the foundation of our hope is certaine and ſure, being built vpon ſo firme a ground as the goſpel is. Now af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this title or inſcription, he commeth vnto the matter itſelfe, and firſt (as I ſaid) beginneth with the accuſation or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in this ſort.</p>
            <q>VVhereas we your Suppliants haue long time indured, and doe dayly receiue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſgraces, impriſonments, and loſſes, to our great impoueriſhing, yea to the vt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter vndoeing of a great many of vs: to the which our afflictions ther is at this time by your <hi>LL.</hi> added the heauy ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Excommunication: and withall we do finde our ſelues dayly (to the inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable greif of our harts) deeper to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the averſion and indignation of his maieſtie, more heavy and greiuous vnto vs, then all our temporal loſſes and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: and all thoſe calamities to haue only their being, in regard only of our Recuſancie and conſtant perſevering in the Religion we haue receiued from our forefathers, as they fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theirs &amp;c.</q>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:7293:13"/>
            <p>In this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint the Petitioner ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth firſt the ſuppoſed greifes and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Recuſants, then alſo the cauſe of their afflictions. Their vexations as he ſetteth them downe, are of ſundry ſorts; in the firſt ranck he placeth ſuch loſſes &amp; diſgraces as they would ſeeme to ſuffer; then they find themſelues greiued with the Eccleſiaſticall cenſure of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: thirdly that his maieſtie doth not ſo fauorably reſpect them, as they would he ſhould.</p>
            <p>The diſgraces that this Petitioner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth of, I cannot certainly ſpeake of, becauſe the complaint is ſo indefinite, without comming to any particulars. It may be that he accompteth it a diſgrace, that Recuſants haue not that grace and credit, that themſelues deſire, or that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the common wealth that they would haue. But that is not properly a diſgracing of them, becauſe nothing is done therin to bring them into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt; but only a not adding of titles or offices to them, for their further reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7293:13"/> who would thinke it fitt that any ſtate ſhould be managed, &amp; the rudder of that ſhip gouerned, by ſuch as are of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Religion to the ſame? So that if this were true, yet is there no iuſt cauſe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint therfore.</p>
            <p>But there are of them but too many in grace and reputation, wherby they haue great meanes to diſcourage the ſimple people ouer whome they haue gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; &amp; to make more obſtinate againſt true obedience to god and Prince, ſuch as are of themſelues but too ready, to ſtart aſide from the right way. And the further that they are fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Soueraigne authority, the more dangerous is any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that is committed to them: becauſe the eye of him, that is to anſwere for the evil that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by bad Officers, which he permitteth or reformeth not, is far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch, that it cannot behold their doinges. It were therfore not only to be wiſhed, but by earneſt praier to be ſued for, that God would in this point more and more lighten the hart of our <hi>most Gratious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:7293:14"/> in any wiſe to take heed that the enemies to Gods truth, haue no credit, I meane for office or autoritie in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth; eſpecially in theſe North parts, where it wil be hard for him truly to knowe what hurt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the truth, what danger to the <hi>ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that that golden ſentence of the wiſeſt man that euer was, and a king too, were written on the back of the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of all Kinges and Princes that haue ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne authority, that it might be in their eie when they ſigne the Billes wherby they grant authoritie to anie vnder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>VVhen the wicked riſe vp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Provreb. 28.</note> 
               <hi>men hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; but when they periſh, the righteous increaſe.</hi> Or that other much like the for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer,<note place="margin">Prou. 25.2.</note> 
               <hi>VVhen the righteous are in authoriy the people reioice, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth rule, the people ſigh.</hi> For there can be no greater hart-breaking to the godly, then to haue wicked men to beare the ſwaie or to them that are zealous for the truth, then when enemies to the ſame, may do what they liſt. Good therfore is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7293:14"/> the councell of Salomon elſewhere, and ſuch as Kinges ſhould carefully follow, forhe no doubt learned it by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. <hi>Take away the wicked from the King (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being partakers vnder him of his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) &amp; his throne ſhalbe eſtabliſhed in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this gracing then, his maieſtie is to haue a ſpecial regard that it be not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any, (if he haue a due care of Gods glorie and the good of his people) but only vpon ſuch as are favorours of the Goſpel, and furtherers of all good; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that moſt godly paterne, which Dauid, a King, ſetteth before al ſuch as are of his ranck,<note place="margin">Pſ. 101.</note> and haue the gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Kingdomes and contries. So that they being ſo oppoſite as they are, to the ſtate as now it is, may not in any diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, if greater authority be not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, then may ſtand ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the furtherance of Gods truth, or with the ſafty of the weale publike.</p>
            <p>What is then the diſgracing here mentioned? Or rather what are the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracinges?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7293:15"/> For ſo he ſpeaketh as if they were diſgraced ſundry waies. If the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner complaine of diſgracings, becauſe ſome few of them, are, after long time of Recuſancy, and after diuers preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions againſt the Lawes of this Realme, and ordinances of this Church, conuented before Authoritie: hee ſhoulde haue called to remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that we holding, yea certainly knowing, that Religion which we profeſſe, to be the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doubted Truth, can doe no leſſe in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of that Truth, then to cal vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that deſpiſe the ſame, to knowe what mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them to reiect the ſame. But when they appeare before authoritie, they are not ſharply rebuked (vnleſſe themſelues giue greater occaſion therof) much leſſe are they by approbrious tearms diſgrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or by any vnſeemlie puniſhments, not fitt and convenient for their perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached: with milde and chriſtian ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations moued to heare ſuch as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues wil chooſe to be farther inſtructed by. And I truſt in al this there is no diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:7293:15"/>
            <p>But I would this Petitioner would look back vnto thoſe dayes not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſince bypaſt. Many of our Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts may reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the daies of Queene Mary, wherin they that complaine ſo much that they are diſgraced (though vntruely) did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by what means they could, diſgrace ſuch Godly Martyrs as came before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by ſtocking and baſe vſage of many, who though they had bin in an error, (which their aduerſaries could neuer proue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them) yet in regard of their paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, degree, or place that they had in the Church &amp; common wealth, ſhould not haue been ſo diſgracefully ſo cruellie delt withall. And what was the beating of Tho: Hinſhaw, and Iohn Milles &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe others with rods? Did not that blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Biſhop Boner diſgrace them thereby as much as he might? To be accoumpted an <hi>Hereticke</hi> is a thing odious &amp; of great diſgrace: yet was it then and ſtill is, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon name that the Romiſh Synagogue beſtowed vpon vs, though nether they nor yet their fathers, could proue any he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7293:16"/> in our doctrine. To be called <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks</hi> is a great reproach: yet dare they ſtaine therwith vs, who are alwaies rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſhew by good warrant and ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimony that we ſwarue not from the true, holy, Catholick and Apoſtolick Church. Thus they who moſt accuſe vs, as if we diſgraced them, may more iuſtly be charged that they diſgrace vs.</p>
            <p>And herein the Petitioner offereth great wrong vnto the <hi>ſtate,</hi> in ſeeking to make the world beleue, that we wiſh the diſgrace of them, for whoſe want of <hi>grace</hi> we rather ſigh and mourne, in that their eies are ſo blinded, &amp; their harts ſo harde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ifeſt light of truth, that they will not vſe any meanes <hi>to trie the ſpirits</hi> (that come in ſecret vnto them) <hi>whether they be of God or not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.1</note> although S. Iohn expreſſly adviſeth all ſo to doe: but rather wittingly yea and wilfully too, they ſuffer their blinde guides to lead the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the bottomleſſe pitt of eternall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. This part therfore of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint may ſeeme rather to tend to this end, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7293:16"/> our <hi>ſtate</hi> be the ſtaine of crueltie may be made odious, to ſuch as will beleeue this Petitioner, and their caſe ſeeme a great deale worſe then it is; rather I ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any iuſt cauſe that is giuen him, to vſe ſuch words.</p>
            <p>And wheras the petition, ſeemeth to make theſe, and the other ſuppoſed vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations after mentioned, to be common to them all, (for I take the <hi>Petitioner</hi> to be a ſuiter for al <hi>Recuſants</hi>) it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that a great number of them are ſo far from ſuffering any diſgrace in reſpect of their Recuſancy, that it is the greateſt ornament they haue among their fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that they are accompted Recuſants; as if they by that name would ſeeme to haue ſome conſcience in Religion, who otherwiſe in all their behauiour, ſhew plainly enough, that they haue nether conſcience, nor honeſtie, but haue vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt of all feare of god &amp; ſhame of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and hauing obtained the report to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants or Romiſh Catholicks, it is a cloake that couereth all faults.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:7293:17"/>
            <p>The next part of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint is touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their impriſonment, wherin as in the former, his accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeemeth to be more generall, then is their impriſonment. For vnleſſe the <hi>Recuſants</hi> in other countries be more obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto Law then in theſe North parts, wherin they haue no regard at all of any Summones, but ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues too contemptuous of all lawfull authoritie: I ſuppoſe J may be bould to ſaie that not the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth <hi>Recuſant</hi> indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth this <hi>vexation.</hi> Nay of ſundry whole families in a manner, perchance not one can be convented. And therfore were it greatlie to be wiſhed, that for the better execution of godlie lawes, ſome more forcible and effectuall order might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the bringing before authoritie, ſuch as yet make a mock of gods truth, deſpiſe all good ordinances, and ſcorne all lawfull authoritie.</p>
            <p>And if anie being found verie obſtinat, in ſo much as nether they will conforme themſelues according to the Chriſtian lawes of this Realme in that caſe proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7293:17"/> nether will, or can giue anie ſound reaſon of ſuch their obſtinacie; nether yet heare others who can inſtruct them (even ſuch of our profeſſion, as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues can beſt like of) be for ſuch contumacie committed to ſome priſon: yet is there not anie Papiſt that hath iuſt cauſe to complaine of ſuch impriſonment, ſeeing that our correction that we laie vpon <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants,</hi> is but with rodds, wheras Papiſts whipp with <hi>Scorpions,</hi> we ſtocke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, we hinder them not, but that they may be releiued of their owne (if they haue it) or by their freinds, if they will beſtow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. We permit them to haue light or fire, or any other thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for them: al which things were denied vnto many of the godly, in the late bloudy perſecution, as ſundry of the <hi>Recuſants</hi> may yet remember. So that we may truly ſay that the litle finger of the Papiſts towards vs, hath bin heauier then our loines towards them: their gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleſt dealing more ſharp for matters of Religion onlie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our greateſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7293:18"/> that we impoſe vpon them.</p>
            <p>But why doe they accompt impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuch a vexation, who thought the moſt cruell death little enough for thoſe of our profeſſion? Let our <hi>Petitioner</hi> call to remembrance the mercyleſſe racking of Miſtreſſe Anne Aſkew by him that was then L. Chancelour, to cauſe her to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray others of her profeſſion; the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous burning of the hande of Tho. Tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, Roſe Alin, and a blinde harper in Queene Maries daies; the forcible draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an arrowe through the fingers of Cutbert Simpſon harde tyed togither ſo that the bloud ſprong out. Let him I ſaie conſider of theſe and ſuch like vnchriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſage of Chriſtian men, whereby they would haue conſtrained them, either to haue accuſed others, or to denie their faith.</p>
            <p>And though the Popiſh rabble, take exception (I know) to the ſtorie wherein theſe things are reported, yet the Author of that booke, brings ſo good proofes of that he writeth, that they who will denie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7293:18"/> theſe things, ſhall rather ſhew a minde they haue to darke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the light of truth, that their ſhame may not appeare, then any good reaſon that they can bring, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire the credit thereof. Theſe ſtories the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being extant, and in eies of al men to read and know, and in the memories of manie men who yet living can teſtifie the truth thereof, may ſtop the mouthes of all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts for complaining of anie great vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for their impriſonment.</p>
            <p>But what woulde the <hi>Petitioner</hi> haue vs to do in this caſe? The <hi>Recuſants</hi> are contrarie to vs in Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſe our Lawes, and breake al godlie ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that are made, for the edifying &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of al his Maieſties ſubiects: they wil not heare, but ſtubbornlie refuſe all councel and teaching, vnleſſe it bee ſuch as their blind guides doe afford them. (I wil not here ſay, they are alſo verie dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the ſtate, for that followeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be diſcuſſed, when I come to the cauſe that this <hi>Petitioner</hi> yeeldeth, why they are thus vexed.) If it be the truth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7293:19"/> that we teach, (as wee are moſt aſſured it is) is it any reaſon we ſhould ſuffer others to be lead away by deceitfull words, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing and ſeducing falſe teachers, &amp; not ſeeke by all meanes we can to reclaime them? It is our part, if poſſible we may, to bring againe to the ſheepfold, thoſe wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſheep. And if gentle &amp; mild per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions will not ſerve, we muſt <hi>compell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> by more ſharpe chaſticement.<note place="margin">Luc. 14.23.</note> This I knowe the moſt milde Papiſtes in the world, would think they ſhould do to the profeſſours of the Goſpel, if authoritie were with them, as now it is with vs.</p>
            <p>We ſee then, that it is not for Papiſts (whoſe crueltie is, I ſuppoſe far greater, againſt ſuch as are not of their profeſſion then any other religion whatſoeuer doth vſe) to complaine of ſuch gentle impriſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment as is impoſed vpon them for Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie; vnleſſe they will thinke it fitt, that in a wel gouerned and ſetled ſtate, lawes may be broken without due puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or offences may be winked at, and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie ſhould be eſteemed to bring ſafty to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7293:19"/> a common wealth, that is peſtred with obſtinate ſubiects. Which to imagine, is to let looſe the raines of libertie, to al diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order &amp; diſobedience, &amp; to trouble the quiet eſtate of a common wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> was once of that minde as himſelfe confeſſeth, that it liked him nothing,<note place="margin">Retract. 2 cap. 5</note> 
               <hi>Vllius ſecularis poteſtatis impetu ſchiſmaticos ad communionem, violentèr, vehementèr<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> arctari; that ſchiſmatickes ſhould by the force of anie ſecular power, be violentlie, and earnestly conſtrained to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate,</hi> meaning in Religion with the godly. But he in that place acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that it was his errour, <hi>quia nondu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertus eram, vel quantum mali eorum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret impunitas, vel quantum eis in melius mutandis conferre poſset diligentia diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinae; becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as yet I had not proued, ether to what audacious miſchiefe their impunitie would draw them, or howe much it would further their amendment to vſe the diligence of diſcipline &amp; ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Father therefore writing to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7293:20"/> 
               <hi>Vincentius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 48.</note> &amp; reporting of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> as we haue found, the Papiſts to be; <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſtae nimiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inquieti ſunt, the Donatiſts</hi> (ſaith he, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> may we ſay) <hi>are too factious &amp; comberſome,</hi> addeth, <hi>quos per ordinatas à Deo poteſtates cohiberi at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> corrigi, mihi non videtur invtile: VVho that by ſuch powers as are ordained of God they ſhould be restrained and corrected, it ſeemeth good to me.</hi> And afterwards hee ſheweth how greatly hee reioiceth at the amendement of manie of them by ſuch ſharpnes, who would not otherwiſe haue beene bettered. To this end alſo he allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth that place of the goſpel,<note place="margin">Luke 14.23</note> 
               <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell ſuch as you finde, to come in. Quia</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vt phrenetici ligantur, ſic Haeretici;</hi> men in error of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are like Lunatick or mad men, they muſt bee bounde and tyed, and as it were by the Phyſick of diſcipline broughte from the deadlye diſeaſe of their dying ſoules. And afterwardes declaring, how diverſe men ſpake of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe occaſions, whereby they were hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered from comming to the Catholicke
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7293:20"/> faith, but being reformed, they gaue thanks to God, who in mercie reclaimed them by ſuch chaſtiſementes: Among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers he bringeth in ſome ſaying, as moſt of our <hi>Recuſants</hi> no doubt may ſaie, <hi>Nos falſis rumoribus terrebamur intrare, quos falſos eſse neſciremus, niſi intraremus, nec intraremus, niſicogeremur. Gratias Domino, qui trepidationem nostram flagel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo abſtulit, expertos docuit quam vana &amp; inania de Eccleſia ſua mendax fama iacta verit:</hi> that is, <hi>wee by falſe reportes vvere ſcarred from entring, which reports vvee ſhould not know to be falſe, vnleſſe wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred: neither would we enter, but being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained. Thanks be vnto the Lord, who by a ſcourge took away our feare, teaching vs by experience, how vaine &amp; falſe rumors, lying fame had ſpread of his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How manie are diſcouraged from our Churches, by vntrue reportes, that we are <hi>ſchiſmaticks,</hi> our Religion is <hi>Hereſie;</hi> to follow vs, is to leaue the Church? We are (ſay they) enemies to good works, we ſpeake againſt faſting and praier; our Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7293:21"/> is a Goſpel of libertie, and manie ſuch like moſt falſe ſlanders, do they ſcatter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad among their favourites: and al to make the ſimple and ignorant afraid, to reſort to our aſſemblies. And when they haue once taken them in the ſnares of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſancie,</hi> and bound them in the chaines of promiſe, oath, &amp; reconciliation, to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; then muſt they not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe heare vs preach, or our <hi>Service</hi> read; they muſt not read our bookes, leaſt their eies being opened, they ſhoulde ſee the myſterie of iniquity, that worketh in, and by Poperie. But as in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Augustines</hi> time manie euen in the cittie of <hi>Hippo,</hi> where he was Biſhop, were by puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment converted from being <hi>Donatists,</hi> &amp; became <hi>Catholickes:</hi> ſo no doubt ſundrie of our <hi>Recuſants,</hi> if good meanes and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient might be obtained, to bring them before authoritie, would eaſily be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to come in, and being come into our Churches, would of themſelues diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the falſe reportes, that they haue hard of our Religion.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:7293:21"/>
            <p>Not only <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is of this minde, but ſundrie other of the <hi>Fathers</hi> too; as <hi>Baſill, Gregorie,</hi> (for his excellencie called the <hi>Divine</hi>) and manie mo ſought for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of ſuch as troubled the Church, by authoritie of the ſword, as may ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie (if it were needful) bee proued out of their owne writings. But to knit vp this matter, of it ſelfe not hard, but by that which hath bin alreadie ſaid, moſt plaine, the Scriptures themſelues afford vs ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient proofe hereof, eſpecially in that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſtorie of <hi>Ioſiah</hi> that good king of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> who after the booke of the Law was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, he read therin before al the people, <hi>&amp; made a covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chro. 34 31.32.</note> 
               <hi>to walk after the Lord. And he cauſed al that were fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Beniamin to ſtande to it.</hi> Marke that it is ſaid <hi>he cauſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that is, the people, to ſtande to the couenant that he had made: and yet it is further to his immortall praiſe recorded of him in Gods Regiſter booke,<note place="margin">33</note> that <hi>he compelled al that vvere found in Iſraell, to ſerue the Lord their God: ſo all his daies they turned
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7293:22"/> not backe from the Lorde God of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May good king <hi>Ioſiah</hi> make his people to ſtand to the covenant, that hee made with God: and may not our godlie King <hi>Iames</hi> doe the like? May he compell them to ſerue the Lorde God, yea and that in ſuch ſort, that all his daies (though no doubt of themſelues prone enough to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie) they durſt not turne backe from the God of their fathers; and ſhall wee ſo manacle the hands of our moſt gracious Soveraigne, or of his Magiſtrates vnder him, that they may not vſe ſuch meanes to force and compell, to the true ſervice of God, as our lawes haue appointed? Shal the king of <hi>Iuda,</hi> haue the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Gods ſpirit to his eternal commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in holy writ, for this his godly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veritie in Gods cauſe: &amp; can it be thought a thing worthie to be complained of, and too ſevere, if the king of <hi>Great Brittaine</hi> ſhall follow his zeale? No, no, the ſame God that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> approued the zeale to Gods glorie, that was in that Mirrour of all
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7293:22"/> Chriſtian Kings, good king <hi>Ioſiah:</hi> the ſame God (I ſay) doth ſtil allow, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in al Princes and Magiſtrates, a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian care, and feruent deſire, to haue his honour aduanced within their domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by ſeting forth and maintaining the true worſhip of God, and compelling all their ſubiects to yeeld therto. Nay if they doe not with care and courage performe this ſeruice, let them remember the time ſhall come, when this voice ſhall ſound full ſhrill in the eare of their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to their great terror,<note place="margin">Luke 16.2.</note> 
               <hi>yeeld an accompt of thy Stewardſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For horribly and ſuddainely will God appeare vnto you (O you mighty monarchs</hi> if you vſe not well your greatnes) <hi>For a hard iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhal they haue that bear rule.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſd. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>For he that is moſt low is worthy mercy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">6.</note> 
               <hi>but the mighty ſhall be mightely tormented;</hi>
               <note place="margin">7.</note> 
               <hi>For he that is Lord ouer al wil ſpare no perſon, nether ſhal he feare any greatnes: for he hath made the ſmall and great, and careth for all alik.</hi>
               <note place="margin">8.</note> 
               <hi>But for the mighty abideth the ſorer triall.</hi> And as God hateth in great
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7293:23"/> ones, al neglect of duty: ſo eſpeciallie to be cold and careleſſe in the thinges that properly concerne his Glorie, he wil not ſuffer vnpuniſhed. For this cauſe, in the ſtories of the Kings ouer Gods people, as there is nothing ſo much commended in them as their zeale in Gods cauſe; ſo are not any their vices in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner ſet downe, (though they were no doubt ſubiect to many, as by the Prophets it may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered) but their Idolatries, or careleſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the ſeruice of God: ſo that it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon ſtaine euen to the good Kings, <hi>the high places, hill-altars, or groues vvere not put downe.</hi> Which glaſſe if Princes would often looke into, they might ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſee, not only that by their office they may, but alſo that of dutie they ought, as <hi>Elias</hi> ſaith he was,<note place="margin">1. Kings 19.10.</note> 
               <hi>to be very ielous for the Lord God of Hoſtes:</hi> &amp; that the maintaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the truth, and aboliſhing of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition is a principall charge belonging vnto them. This appeareth plainelie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, in that it is required of kings, that they be much exerciſed in Gods booke,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7293:23"/> 
               <hi>He ſhal read therin all the daies of his life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17.19</note> 
               <hi>that he may learne to feare the Lord his God, and to keep all the words of this lawe, and theſe ordinances</hi> (not to knowe them onlie) <hi>for to doe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the laſt of the <hi>vexations</hi> (for ſo he tearmeth their milde and meeke cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections) which hee ſpeaketh of, of this ranke, is their <hi>loſſes.</hi> And in deed, <hi>Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants</hi> haue great and grievous <hi>loſses,</hi> (I confeſſe) and ſuch, as if they could conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of them aright, would make the haire of their heads to ſtand on end, and their verie harts to melt and bleed for ſorrow. <hi>Oh that they were wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.29 Luke 19.42</note> 
               <hi>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this, they would conſider their lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end. O if they had knowne at the leaſt in this their day, thoſe things which belong vnto their peace: but nowe are they hid fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their eies.</hi> They complaine of their <hi>vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1.31. Ier. 17.10. Eſa. 50.11.</note> but they are moſt of all vexed with their own inventions; and their fruitleſſe &amp; wicked imaginations, are chiefe cauſe of their endleſſe ſorrow.</p>
            <p>They haue <hi>loſſes;</hi> it is moſt true. They haue
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7293:24"/> loſt the reputation of dutifull ſubiects. And how can it be otherwiſe, ſince they haue vowed themſelues to the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of him, who is an enemie to al <hi>Soueraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> beſides his owne.<note place="margin">Mat. 6.24</note> 
               <hi>As noe man can ſerue two maſters</hi> (for ſo our Sauiour Chriſt telleth vs) <hi>For either he ſhall hate the one and loue the other, or elſe ſhall he leane to the one and deſpiſe the other:</hi> ſo noe man certainely, can promiſe &amp; performe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to two ſuch Monarches, as are of that nature, that the one of them over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth the ſtate of the other. They who are ſubiect to the <hi>Romiſh Biſhop,</hi> whoſe greateſt care is to maintain ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and his owne pride, that he may be exalted aboue the greateſt Potentats vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth: can neuer truely ſerue him (whatſoeuer in words they do pretend) who oppoſeth himſelfe againſt all ſuch will-worſhips, and will not ſubeict his Soueraigne power, to the ambitious wil of that <hi>Romiſh Preiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea they haue loſt the harts of dutiful Subiects; For the <hi>Romiſh Theef</hi> who rob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7293:24"/> God of his honour, Princes of their obedience, and ſubiects of their ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath by his inchantments ſtole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away the harts of <hi>Recuſants</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their natural Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and dread Soveraignes. So that they reſt vpon his wil, and do but waite for his commandement, if it be, to oppoſe them ſelues againſt their friends, their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, yea and their Natiue Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try too. For <hi>Recuſants</hi> are not to bee reckoned in that ranke, neither are they acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted of among the Papiſts themſelues, vntil they haue promiſed obedience vnto him, who vnder colour of beeing Heade of the Church (for that vniuſt title hee challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth) robbeth the greateſt members of the Church, of their due honour and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageance.</p>
            <p>They leeſe alſo the benefit of the <hi>word,</hi> which in our Churches ſoundeth in ſuch a tongue &amp; language, as the ignoranteſt may vnderſtand, ſo that they therby may be edified and inſtructed, their ſoules fed and nouriſhed to eternall life: yea that they may haue that <hi>ſword of the Spirit</hi> in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7293:25"/> readines, the better to be inabled, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the daungerous aſſaultes of Satan. And by this loſſe of the <hi>word of God,</hi> they are alſo deprived of the knowledge of the truth, and of the true ſervice of God; they make ſhipwracke of faith; they want the true light of conſcience, the ſweete com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of Gods moſt comfortable promiſes. Theſe (I ſay) and manie ſuch like heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie graces they leeſe, and in recompence of theſe ſo great <hi>loſſes,</hi> they gaine from <hi>Rome</hi> (if it may be called gaine, which they buy with ſo deere a price as thoſe things coſt them, and with ſo evident pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril to their ſoules,) they gaine (I ſay) <hi>Pardons, Agnus-Deis, bleſſed graines, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated croſſes,</hi> with other ſuch traſh &amp; trumperie, things of no worth; though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed by them moſt deere &amp; precious, if anie their ſeducers bring them newes from <hi>Rome,</hi> telling them the <hi>holy Father,</hi> himſelfe did conſecrate the ſame, &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his holie hands over them.</p>
            <p>But theſe are not the <hi>loſſes</hi> that grieue our <hi>Recuſants</hi> or wherof the <hi>Petitioner</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:7293:25"/> complaineth. <hi>we dayly receiue loſſes (ſay they) to our great impoueriſhing, yea to the vndoeing of a great many of vs.</hi> Firſt for the common ſort who are the greateſt number, for ought I knowe, few of them are any way touched to their <hi>loſſe.</hi> Some few, and thoſe very few indeed, are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time conuented, perchance alſo impriſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their great ſtubbornnes, &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue example that they giue of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience. But this withall I dare affirme, that many of them gaine by their <hi>Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> ſo farr are they from leeſing therby. For hauing no good meane to liue, there are that ſort themſelues with theſe diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient perſones obtaineing therby bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter maintenance, then otherwiſe their owne ſtate would afford them.</p>
            <p>I could alſo name if I would one, who (as I haue credibly hard) being impriſoned in <hi>Yorke Caſtle,</hi> liued ſo by this <hi>loſse,</hi> that he gained wherby to purchaſe la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d worth one hundred pound by the yeare. It is a common thing and vſed of very many of good reckoning, vnder colour of their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7293:26"/> trouble for their <hi>Recuſancy,</hi> to leſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their charge, and liue far vnder that ſtate, that their anceſtors haue heretofore liued &amp; they might liue in ſaueing much therby, for ought the world can iudge, whether to ſome good purpoſe or not, the Lord beſt knoweth. Yea that is alſo many times a colourable pretence, for racking of rents, and dealing hardly, ether with Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants or with any other, with whom they haue to deale.</p>
            <p>So that if ſome of the greater ſort doe pay to his <hi>Maieſties</hi> coffers ſomwhat: yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many of them find means enough to make that paiment verie litle in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of that ſhould be paid, and more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that litle, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> raiſe by ſuch means as J haue mentioned, to keep them from <hi>loſse.</hi> Our <hi>Petitioner</hi> therfore cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaid vs, that generally their <hi>loſse</hi> is ſuch as that they need ſo to complaine of <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſhing,</hi> much leſſe of <hi>vtter vndoing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But grant their <hi>loſses</hi> to be greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are. I am ſure they are no heauier then the law it ſelfe doth impoſe; no not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7293:26"/> ſo ſharp by farr. And if any man wil think our lawes to be too ſeuere, he muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that nether we only, nether firſt of all, haue made Pecuniarie puniſhments to reſtraine ſuch as are of contrarie Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.<note place="margin">Epiſt. 50.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> liketh wel of a lawe made by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> that godly Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, generally againſt <hi>all Hereticks, that their Biſhops or Clerks wherſoeuer they were found ſhould be finde in ten pounds,</hi> &amp; wiſheth it might be more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie made againſt the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> becauſe they denied themſelues to be <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe of ſome outrages after co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> a more ſharp law was decreed, that they who were of that ſect, ſhould be pu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iſhed by the <hi>purſe, But their Biſhops or Miniſters ſhould be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed: vt ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tae immanitatis haereſis Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtarum; (cui crudeliùs parci videbatur qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſa ſaeuicbat) non tantum violentae eſſe, ſed omnino eſse non ſineretur impunè:</hi> that is, <hi>That the Hereſie of the Donatists being of ſo great crueltie that the ſparing therof might well ſeeme to be greater cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7293:27"/> ſhould not only not be ſuffered to be ſo fierce, but not to be at al vnpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iſhed.</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſufficiently it appeareth tſtat Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Princes, giue no iuſt cauſe to <hi>Recuſants</hi> of complaint, if by the purſe, or other moderate and reſonable puniſhments, they doe not only reſtraine the overbold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſuch as dare infringe their godlie lawes, but alſo force the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come to their Churches,</p>
            <p>Hither to we haue ſeene that the <hi>loſses</hi> of <hi>Recuſants</hi> are not ſo greate as they would haue them eſteemed; and though they were ſuch; it is plaine they were iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable, before anie of indifferent iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But what are the <hi>loſſes</hi> that <hi>Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants</hi> can ſpeake of, in reſpect of the <hi>loſse,</hi> not of ſome goods onlie, but of libertie alſo, and of life too? In the Perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that was in the daies of <hi>Queene Mary,</hi> againſt the Profeſſours of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the fathers and mothers <hi>loſt</hi> their children? the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren their parents, the huſbands <hi>loſt</hi> their wiues, and wiues their huſbands, &amp; dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friends were taken the one, from the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7293:27"/> other. Theſe were <hi>loſſes</hi> indeede, and ſuch as were verie grievous &amp; gaue iuſt cauſe of complaint. But to haue ſome reſtraint of libertie, or a ſmal Pecuniarie puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is no heavy burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beare for conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>In the late daies of perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which euen now I ſpake of, a great number of godlie Martyrs woulde haue accompted ſuch <hi>diſgraces</hi> as are here complained of, great glorie, ſuch <hi>impriſonment,</hi> great li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie and freedome, yea ſuch <hi>loſses,</hi> an exceeding great gaine; if in a meane ſtate of life, though in priſon, they might haue beene free to ſerue their God. It cannot cannot therfore but ſeeme a thing to me very ſtrange, &amp; to all other too of indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent iudgment, that they, who when they had the Law and the ſword in their owne handes, omitted almoſt no kinde of crueltie, againſt ſuch as vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds and ſuch as their adverſaries themſelues could not tel how to diſproue, diſſented from them in Religion; ſhould now vpon ſo light occaſion, make ſo great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7293:28"/> as if ſome great cruelty were ſhewed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. And whereas then theſe <hi>impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments</hi> and <hi>loſſes,</hi> were laid vpon al that they could heare of, that loued the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, with ſharpe inquirie and cruel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining of manie, to accuſe others: yet now we know, and dailie ſee before our eies, ſundrie whom we know to be <hi>Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants,</hi> and yet doe not vſe that extremitie againſt them that wee might but rather looke for their converſion, being nothing ſo forwarde to take them, as they were to burne vs.</p>
            <p>But by whom haue our <hi>Recuſants</hi> ſuch <hi>loſſes,</hi> as are to the <hi>impoveriſhing, yea the vtter vndoing of many of them?</hi> The kings coffers get not much, as hath bin ſhewed and that which goeth that waie, is taken of ſuch as are wel able to pay. If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their <hi>loſſes</hi> be ſo great, let them conſider vvell with themſeues by whom their <hi>loſſe</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. The <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> the <hi>Great Masters</hi> of al out <hi>Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</hi> how proud they are in their followers, apparell, and diet, &amp; in things that belong vnto them,<note place="margin">Quod lib.</note> 
               <hi>VVilliam VVatſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:7293:28"/> that <hi>traiterous Preiſt,</hi> and other <hi>Popiſh Preiſts</hi> can tell vs, in a Memoriall of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations (thought to be deviſed by one <hi>Fiſher</hi>) in the 4 <hi>Paragraph</hi> of it,<note place="margin">Reply to Fa. Parſons Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell. fol. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> thus ſaith <hi>Noe Ieſuit goeth to viſit any in England, or trauelleth from on place to another, but he is richly appareled, and atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on with a great traine of ſeruants, as if he were a Baron or a Earle.</hi> And the <hi>Reply of Parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Libell</hi> telleth vs of <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Garnett,</hi> whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes could not be leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 500. <hi>pounds</hi> by the yeare, And of Maſter Iohn Gerard the worth of whoſe apparel he ſhameth to report, whoſe Geldings alſo were of great price and many. And one <hi>Oldcorne</hi> whom he calleth but a <hi>pety Ieſuite,</hi> he knoweth his apparell to be ſeldome leſſe worth then 30. or 40.<note place="margin">yea a Ieſuite girdle and ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers of <hi>30l</hi> price. Letters of A. C. p. <hi>65</hi>
               </note> pound and he had 8 good Geldings at one time. I would that our <hi>Petitioner</hi> ſhould conſider, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c maintenance muſt be had for theſe irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular <hi>Regular</hi> ſpendthrifts, and prodigall lauiſhers of other mens goods: is it not from <hi>Recuſants?</hi> If it be; let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not charg the ſtate with their <hi>loſſes,</hi> but their owne
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7293:29"/> Traiterous harts who vpon their charge maintaine ſuch vnprofitable burdens of of the Common-wealth, ſuch dangerous Canker wormes to the ſtate.</p>
            <p>Yea and further the ſame reply telleth vs that in the Colledge of Ieſuits at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demars (notwithſtanding all their Penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the King and others)</hi> there <hi>be few Engliſh youthes there, whoſe parents doe not largly pay for their educations; nether can any poore youth be admitted thither (for all their penſions) but he muſt either haue anual ſtipe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of</hi> 20. <hi>markes plus minus by the yeare, or</hi> 40. 50. <hi>or</hi> 60. <hi>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in groſſe ſumme.</hi> Such continual portions to be beſtowed vpon <hi>Recuſants</hi> Children ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to their <hi>Seminaries,</hi> are indeed the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſhing of them,</hi> nay the cauſe of a great want in the vvhole Realme, from which ſo many ſummes are tranſported. In the meane ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haue the <hi>Prieſts</hi> who tel vs theſe tales nothing? They haue bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to fill, and backes to cloath, and that is done not of the worſt. Manie a wife robbing and vndoing their owne Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7293:29"/> to cheriſh (ſuch is their hot deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) theſe their <hi>Corner-friends;</hi> who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are ſeene abroad, are taken &amp; repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed for <hi>Courtiers</hi> and <hi>Gallants, VVatſon</hi> &amp; others of them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine that the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> are nothing liberall to them. Of whom then haue they their finding? Of whom, but of <hi>Recuſants?</hi> Theſe are great meanes to <hi>impoveriſh</hi> men of good abilitie, to mainetaine ſuch a number of <hi>Caterpillers</hi> or <hi>Graſhoppers</hi> worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe of <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides theſe things <hi>VVilliam VVatſon</hi> in the <hi>Quodlibets,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Reply</hi> to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>libell</hi> eſpecially telleth vs, that they haue manie moe waies to get from <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants:</hi> there are <hi>Legacies in Pios vſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reply fol. 24.</note> 
               <hi>yeerely almes, extraordinarie gifts, reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions de bonis incertis, diſpenſations in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers caſes, alienations, advowſons, &amp;c.</hi> and that the <hi>Legacies in Pios Vſus</hi> haue within few years come to 2000. or 3000. pound. And declareth alſo how <hi>Iohn Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi> a <hi>Ieſuit</hi> got of one <hi>Gentl.</hi> at one time 200. pound, at another time 700, and the beſtowing of an 100. pound by yeere: of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7293:30"/> another 160. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, of another 500. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; of a Gent. &amp; his Mother 1000. marks. Is not this good getting for one man? I neede not here report what is teſtified in the <hi>Quodlibets</hi> concerning many notable pillings of men and women by the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> and eſpeciallie by that cheating Letcher <hi>Gerrard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quod lib. 2 art. 5. Quod. lib. 3 art. 10.</note> who beſides his ordinarie couſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of women, (with which ſex hee was moſt intimat,) drew 3500<hi rend="sup">li</hi>. at one clap from one man. But verie probably wee maie thinke, that if not all, yet much of that that our <hi>Engliſh men</hi> haue abroade, commeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our <hi>Recuſants,</hi> &amp; no doubt, ſuch as are at home are nouriſhed by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Is it any maruel if the very vaines of their riches bee drawne,<note place="margin">Quodlib. 3. art. 10. <hi>From H. Dru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> 3500 <hi>A. Rowſe</hi> 1000<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. <hi>E. VVolpool.</hi> 1000<hi rend="sup">••</hi>. <hi>Hudleſtone.</hi> 1000<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. <hi>&amp;c. Anat. of T.</hi> B. l. 3. <hi>adviſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> who haue ſo manie <hi>Horſteaches</hi> to ſucke the ſame? Adde vnto theſe their <hi>Holy exerciſes,</hi> whereof the <hi>Prieſts</hi> make report, &amp; you ſhal finde the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> the moſt cunning <hi>cony catchers.</hi> I thinke in the world to abuſe folke and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin them of their wealth.</p>
            <p>So that our <hi>Recuſants</hi> we ſee, maie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede by <hi>Ieſuits</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> marvelouſly
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:7293:30"/> be <hi>impoveriſhed,</hi> though ſlowe enough they be, to beare anie burdens of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</hi> For when ſuch things are demanded of them, then wil they alleage their paiments they make to the Prince, when he ſhall perchance not get the ſixt part of that which is their due. But as if nothing were gotten from them, but that which by godlie Lawes is iuſtlie clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from ſome few of them, for their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate recuſancie, they crie out of their <hi>loſses</hi> and <hi>impoveriſhing,</hi> yea of their <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing,</hi> as if what the <hi>Prince</hi> hath, or the <hi>Law</hi> requireth of them, went to a wrong purſe: but what <hi>Traiterous ſeducers</hi> get from them, be it much more, is al wel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed.</p>
            <p>Wee ſee then that the penalties that Law impoſeth are not ſo grieuous as the <hi>Petitioner</hi> woulde it ſhould bee thought: they are not impoſed vpon manie, and that they ſhould bee more impoſed then they are it is neceſſarie; and hath exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from former ages, with the godly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7293:31"/> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> And to bee ſhort it is moſt evident, that the fauour that they beare to the Enemies of God and the State, is greater cauſe of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſhing, yea and of the vndoing of a great number of them, then is anie exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Law againſt them, onlie in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their <hi>Recuſancie.</hi> For if their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Law, which is to great in them, by penalties be, if not reformed, yet cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed; their obſtinacie therein, not their <hi>Recuſancie,</hi> is fined.</p>
            <q>To the which our afflictions there is at this time added by your LL. the heavie cenſure of Excommunication.</q>
            <p>This is the <hi>ſeconde part</hi> of the <hi>Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> complaint, that <hi>Recuſants</hi> be <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated.</hi> And is this <hi>Cenſure</hi> ſo <hi>heavie</hi> vnto <hi>Recuſants.</hi> They willinglie &amp; obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natlie refuſe our Aſſemblies, flie from our <hi>Churches,</hi> diſdaine our praiers, contemne our adminiſtration of <hi>Sacraments;</hi> to be ſhort they wil be none of vs, and yet are grieued that they are not accompted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs. Nay when they heare of their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7293:31"/> 
               <hi>Excommunication,</hi> there are of them that can ſaie, it is their deſire ſo to be; they are euen as they would be. And yet to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat the vexations that <hi>Recuſants</hi> ſuffer, this is added as a thing that much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth them, that they are <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> this is now a <hi>heavy cenſure.</hi> What, is it more grievous that our <hi>Biſhops</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce them to be none of our Church then that themſelues abandon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from the ſame? May they diſpiſe all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, abuſe all authoritie, breake al good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſeperate themſelues from God and godlie Exerciſes of our Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and our <hi>Biſhops</hi> &amp; wee looke on in the meane time, and vſe no diſcipline to reforme diſordered perſons?</p>
            <p>I am glad that <hi>Excommunicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> is now iudged to be a <hi>heavy cenſure,</hi> euen that <hi>excommunication</hi> that is done orderlie &amp; as it ought to be; the parties vpon whom it is to be inflicted, being iudicially called and that vnto ſuch places, as they maie come without danger. For hereby appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth what iuſt occaſion of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint thoſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7293:32"/> 
               <hi>Romiſh Cenſures</hi> haue giuen to vs, who haue ere novv Interdicted this <hi>Realme, Excommunicated</hi> our <hi>Princes,</hi> not being their lawfull iudges,<note place="margin">Euen as at this time they deale with the <hi>ſtate of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice.</hi>
               </note> not calling them iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially to place conuenient, not hearing no not careing to heare what they could ſay in their defence. Jt ſeemeth they are of that mind that whatſoeuer thoſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>Cenſures of Rome</hi> doe againſt vs, muſt go for good, and whatſoeuer wee doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, muſt be holden too ſevere and heauy. A <hi>Heavie Cenſure</hi> (I warrant you) to put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the Church, whom vve ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by no meanes faire or fowle bring to the Church, much like as if truantlie and ſtubburne Schollers ſhould ſay they find themſelues greiued, becauſe their Maſter chargeth them to come no more to Schole, or if a loitering lubber ſhould finde fault, that he is not ſet to worke.</p>
            <p>But if this lavv were ſo executed as it might be, it would indeed be much the heauier and giue them inſter cauſe ether of complaint, or of amendment. For (as I take it) they who ſtand <hi>excommunicate,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:7293:32"/> are depriued of all benefit of Subiects, or of defence by Law, againſt ſuch wrongs as are offered vnto them. But we are not of the Popiſh ſpirite, to ſeeke by all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe &amp; malice, to wreake them, as they would vs. No, ſome of vs are rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſuffer their manie wrongs, then to offer them ſuch hard meaſure. Neither doe I remember, that I haue euer hard that aduantage taken againſt anie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſauing that in <hi>Northumberland</hi> (as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported) one <hi>Recuſant</hi> thought to plead that againſt another of that Sect: But he againſt whom it ſhould be pleaded, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of his purpoſe, came to the Church, and ſo auoided his intent. But to end this point, we know &amp; confeſſe that the <hi>Cenſure</hi> of <hi>Excommunicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> is indeed <hi>heavy</hi> and grieuous vnto the godlie, and ſuch as are of the Church: but becauſe <hi>Recuſants</hi> are out of our Churches, and will not be of our Aſſemblies, this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint therefore is of it ſelfe nothing, but added onlie as a <hi>cipher</hi> to make the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>vexations</hi> ſeeme greater.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:7293:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The third vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> that this <hi>Petitioner</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaineth of, is vttered in theſe wordes: <hi>and withall we doe finde our ſelues dayly (to the inexplicable griefe of our harts) dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to incurre the averſion and indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Maieſtie, more heavie and grievous vnto vs, then all our temporall loſſes &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</hi> In deed if this be conſidered as it ought to be, it is iuſt cauſe of <hi>griefe.</hi> For the <hi>wiſest</hi> that euer was, hath ſet it down in writing,<note place="margin">Prov. 19. i2</note> that, <hi>The kings wrath is as the roaring of a Lyon:</hi> as on the other ſide, <hi>his favour is like the dew vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the graſſe.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">Prov. 20.2.</note> 
               <hi>The feare of the king, is like the roaring of a Lyon, he that provoketh him to anger, ſinneth againſt his owne ſoule.</hi> And yet againe in another place,<note place="margin">Pro. 16.14.</note> 
               <hi>The wrath of a king is as meſse<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers of death; but a wiſe man will pacifie it.</hi> In the later of which places we ſee, what aduice king <hi>Salomon</hi> giueth vnto them, who feele the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their <hi>Soveraigne, heavie and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous;</hi> namelie, that they if they be <hi>wiſe,</hi> ſhoulde frame themſelues to <hi>pacifie</hi> the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:7293:33"/>
            <p>His <hi>averſion</hi> (you ſaie) and <hi>indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is <hi>grievous.</hi> Indeed <hi>Recuſants</hi> haue iuſt cauſe to feare it. For if <hi>his Maieſty</hi> ſhould deale according to rigour of Law, as <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants</hi> diuerſe times prouoke him to do, not onlie by their ſtubbornes, but alſo by their ſtrange and ſawcie, yea and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous attempts: their caſe would bee yet much harder then hitherto it hath been, and their puniſhments more ſharpe.</p>
            <p>But you are <hi>grieved</hi> you ſaie, how ſhal your <hi>griefe</hi> be remedied? Muſt the <hi>king</hi> yeeld vnto your vnlawfull &amp; vnchriſtian deſire, to grant <hi>Toleratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> Is it not rather fit that you ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſcend to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt godlie and Chriſtian laws, &amp; agree with him in his moſt holie Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? His Religion is ſuch, as is directlie op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to Popiſh ſuperſtitions and <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> neither maie he, vnleſſe he wil incur gods diſpleaſure, permit or ſuffer any Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh abominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s within his dominions, as perchance maie hereafter bee ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlie proued, when I come to the thirde general point of this <hi>Petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Seeing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7293:34"/> he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not condeſcend to you, vnleſſe he wil goe againſt the light of his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and neglect the neceſſarie dutie of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> king: if you will looke for eaſe of your <hi>griefe,</hi> it is reaſon you conforme your ſelues to his godlie lawes.</p>
            <p>And that the rather, becauſe <hi>Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants</hi> verie iuſtly giue cauſe of <hi>his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties averſion &amp; indignation,</hi> in that they hold a contrarie Religion, his being ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falliblie grounded vpon Gods vndoubted <hi>written VVord;</hi> they thinke themſelues bound to obey the Popes will, though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>King</hi> and this <hi>State,</hi> vowing their ſeruice vnto that prowd &amp; preſump<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous <hi>Man of ſinne,</hi> that abuſeth all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie &amp; Maieſtie whatſoeuer.<note place="margin">Lib. ſacr. Ceremon.</note> He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>Emperours</hi> &amp; kings hold his ſtirrup, lead his horſe, naie to be his foot ſtooles, to powre the water when hee waſheth, to ſerue him at his table, to kiſſe his feet, and in Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels to ſit no higher then his feet;<note place="margin">Pontifical. de inaug. Reg.</note> yea, he maketh them ſweare <hi>Canonical o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> to him. He taketh vpon him to depoſe them at his pleaſure, to giue their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:7293:34"/> right &amp; inheritance to whom it pleaſeth him, to diſcharge ſubiects of oath &amp; obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Hath <hi>his Maieſtie,</hi> or anie other Prince that hath anie wiſe care of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, anie cauſe to like or loue ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects?</p>
            <p>Your anſwere I knowe is ready, that you wilbe ſubiect to the Pope for <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> onlie. But who ſhall be iudge therin; the <hi>Pope</hi> or you? If he ſaith that it belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the cauſe of Religion to depoſe an <hi>Hereticke,</hi> (as he tearmeth all that loue the Goſpel) you dare not ſay, it is not ſo. In ſuch caſe his Maieſtie hath noe cauſe to hope wel of ſo doubtful ſubiects. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you would haue his cheerfull cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, ioine not with him who is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimy to our gracious Soueraigne, and al others that maintaine the truth. Nether can your words perſwade vs, that your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend no further then you promiſe, ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as you retaine and maintaine among you <hi>Ieſuits and Priests</hi> ſuch firebrands of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife, &amp; trumpets of Rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; of whoſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7293:35"/> miſchieuous purpoſes and practiſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this their Natiue countrie, as the <hi>Prieſts in their many bookes extant</hi> are good witneſſes againſt the <hi>Ieſuits;</hi> ſo the late conſpiracie of <hi>VVatſon,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſcheiuous intents and meanings by them before plotted and intended, do plainlie declare, how dangerous your <hi>Priests</hi> are too. Is it not then for the ſafty of his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> to haue <hi>indignation</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe Hoaſts, that intertaine ſuch gueſts?</p>
            <p>Moreouer his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> hath yet great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cauſe of <hi>indignation,</hi> when he calleth to rememberance, how wholy the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> charge ſubiects, to honour &amp; obey their Kings and Princes. <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. i.</note> 
               <hi>For there is noe power but of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; the powers that be, are ordained of God. &amp;c.</hi> And the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> vvriting vnto <hi>Titus, put them (of Creta,</hi> ſaith he) <hi>in remembrance, that they be ſubiect vnto principalities and powers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3. i.</note> 
               <hi>and that they be obedient. S. Peter</hi> likwiſe, <hi>ſubmit your ſelues to al manner ordinance
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7293:35"/> of man, for the Lords ſake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>whether it be vnto the King, as vnto the ſuperiour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">14.</note> 
               <hi>or vnto gouernours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">17.</note> 
               <hi>as vnto them that are ſent of him. Feare God, Honour the King.</hi> Theſe I ſaie, and many ſuch like places, proue that we owe this duty to him.</p>
            <p>But for the <hi>Pope</hi> there is not one, I ſay not one teſtimonie in all the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> to proue that <hi>vniuerſall</hi> power that he challengeth; <hi>vniuerſall</hi> J tearme it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he extendeth his iuriſdiction, by force and ſubtletie, not onlie ouer al Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and cauſes <hi>Eccleſiasticall,</hi> in al places whatſoeuer, but alſo medleth ſo far with Princes too, that they who are vnder his ſlaviſh obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, may not but by his leaue preſume to enter vpon their lawful right and inheritance. Yet this man, whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoritie is ſo lawleſſe, and ſo deſtitute of all good ground, beareth ſo great a ſwaie in the harts of <hi>Recuſants,</hi> that if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, they eaſily forget all duty and ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, that the law of God and man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Giue therfore to Caeſar the things that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.2.</note>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:7293:36"/> 
               <hi>are Caeſars, and giue vnto God thoſe things which are gods.</hi> Rob not Potentates and Princes of their authoritie, deny the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not their due obedience, acknowledge not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny aboue them, or equall to them, in the affaiers of their owne dominis. By ſuch meanes you ſhal more perſwade his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> and aſſure him of your louing and loiall affections, then by al the faire ſhew of words wherwith you gloze.</p>
            <p>Nether is there any cauſe you ſhould feare, to caſt of your yoke of bondage &amp; ſeruitude to that <hi>Romiſh Preiſt,</hi> who (as I ſaid) hath not any warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of gods word, to take vpon him as <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Church.</hi> The firſt that gott that title was <hi>Boniface the</hi> 3. who was at the leaſt 600. yeares after <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and he that gaue that ſuperiority, was that wicked <hi>Phocas,</hi> who murdered his <hi>Maſter</hi> to obtaine the <hi>Empire.</hi> He it was that granted, <hi>Vt Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Romanus, vocaretur, &amp; haberetur ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put omnium Eccleſiarum, that the Biſhop of Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plat in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naf. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould be counted and called head of all Churches,</hi> as <hi>Platina</hi> and other ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7293:36"/> report. The <hi>Headſhip</hi> ouer the <hi>Church</hi> being thus obtained, by the meanes of that wicked <hi>Emperour; Boniface</hi> the 8. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards,<note place="margin">Benevenuti Auguſt. in Alberto.</note> he who was called <hi>papa famo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, The famous Pope,</hi> not for any good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes I warrant you, and <hi>Magnificus tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſacerdotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, The ſtately Tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Prieſts,</hi> (for indeed he vſed them very cruelly, ſo did he Princes too) he who appearing on day like a <hi>Pope,</hi> the next day attired as <hi>Emperour,</hi> with the <hi>Imperiall diade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> on his head, &amp; a ſword by his ſilly ſide, cried, <hi>Ego ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Caeſar, I am Emperour</hi> (for he thought the matter being ſo vnlikelie, noe man would haue beleeued that he was <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> vnleſſe he ſpak ſo) others (as <hi>Friar Ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>och</hi>) report his words thus,<note place="margin">Rioch in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berto.</note> 
               <hi>Ego ſolus Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, I am only Emperour;</hi> he I ſay cauſed it to be holden a thing <hi>de neceſsitate ſalutis neceſſarie to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beleeue the Church of Rome to be the head of all Churches.</hi> Which alſo more then 120. yeares after was decreed in the <hi>Councell of Florence.</hi> Wherby it appeareth, that it is very late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet downe to be a matter of <hi>faith</hi> &amp; that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7293:37"/> it may evede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly therby be gathered, that the <hi>Popes ſupremacie</hi> is not by Gods law, but by mans deuiſe eſtabliſhed, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that it may by man alſo be reiected.</p>
            <p>Jf therfore <hi>Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> vvil ſtil be ſlaues to that <hi>Romiſh Prieſt,</hi> who vſurpeth Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie vvithout anie warrant, &amp; vvhoſe <hi>headſhip</hi> over the Church, vvas not need<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful to be beleeued vntil within theſe 160 yeares or there about; then may vve iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie charge them, to be the cauſers of their owne <hi>griefs,</hi> &amp; the workers of their owne vvoe, in that they are obedient to a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power,</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſmale or rather no ground, if he command the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: againſt that dutie that the lavve of <hi>Nature,</hi> the lavv of <hi>Nations,</hi> and the Lavv of God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of al <hi>Subiects.</hi> The Petitioner ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in vaine maketh their caſe herein ſo lamentable, and their greife ſo great, as if nothing were greater corſiue or diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to them, then the vvant of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties</hi> fauour, if to obtaine it, they vvill not yeeld to that, which ſo eaſilie, ſo law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, ſo honeſtlie may be done: yea which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7293:37"/> of neceſſitie and in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience they ought to doe: I meane if abandoning al <hi>forraine Power</hi> whatſoever, that wil not wholly imploy and vowe their ſeruice to their &amp; our <hi>Dread Soueraigne.</hi> For whatſoever they pretend to be, or how much ſoever they ſay they wil doe in his cauſe, if like the <hi>Gadits, they had faces like lions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chro. 12.8.</note> 
               <hi>and were like the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oes in the mountaines in ſwiftnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">14.</note> 
               <hi>If one of the leaſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could reſiſt a hundred, and the greateſt a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> yet is it not for his Maieſtie to truſt any but ſuch as are like to them of <hi>Zabulon</hi> mentioned in that chapter,<note place="margin">33.</note> 
               <hi>that had not a double hart.</hi> One hart for the <hi>King,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Pope, I like not.</p>
            <p>Thus haue we ſeene, how they (in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the perſecutions which they haue laid vpon others) complaine of eaſe and make as if their burdens were not to be borne, though vpon others they did lay heavier by many degrees. Now let vs conſider to what cauſe they impute all theſe vexations. <hi>And all theſe calamities to haue only their being, in regard only of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7293:38"/> our Recuſancie</hi> (ſaith this Petitioner) <hi>and conſtant perſeuering in the Religion wee haue receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our forefathers, as they from theirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſeemeth to touch two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of theiſe their ſuppoſed <hi>vexations;</hi> The one is their <hi>Recuſancy,</hi> the other their <hi>Constancy.</hi> Their <hi>Recuſancy</hi> is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to be partakars with vs in the <hi>word, Sacraments, and Praiers,</hi> and ſuch excerciſes of our Religion: the other is a Reſolute perſeuerance in their Poperie.</p>
            <p>It ought not ſeeme ſtrange vnto <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> if for <hi>Recuſancy</hi> onlie, they indure the griefes before mentioned, ſince they for matter of <hi>Religion</hi> onlie, haue tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized in moſt grieuous manner, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented euen vnto death, farre better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anie of them that I heare of. Was it not a common ſnare to take al true Profeſſours of the Goſpell in thoſe bloodie daies of <hi>Queen Mary, what ſay you to the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the altar?</hi> And if therin they woulde not beleiue as they did, and ſay as they ſaid (though their abſurditie in ihat point
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:7293:38"/> was exceeding groſſe) vvas it not then thought cauſe ſufficient to bring them to the fire and ſtake. The ſtories are for this point ſo manie, that I need not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularlie to alleadge anie: they are ſo teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified moſt of them in their <hi>Biſhops</hi> owne <hi>Registers,</hi> and by ſo good proofe, as that iuſtlie they cannot be doubted of.</p>
            <p>Yea hath it not bin cauſe ſufficient in the times of Poperie, greiuouſlie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute ſuch as onlie had, or hard read vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, ſome peice of <hi>Scripture</hi> in the Engliſh tongue? Lett the <hi>Regiſter booke of Longland Biſhop of Lincolne,</hi> teſtifie hearin againſt ſuch as will not beleeue the truth: For their ſhal they finde that <hi>An.</hi> 1521. manie had that obiected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as ſufficient cauſe of ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful penance or cruel death. Nether was anie matter of <hi>State,</hi> but of <hi>Religion</hi> only laid to the Charge of <hi>Richard Baifeild</hi> ſomtime <hi>Monke of Bury,</hi> but after a <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> for the truth of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> moſt cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie dealt withal in the <hi>Lollards</hi> tower, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hanged by the necke, middle, &amp; legs,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7293:39"/> his hands alſo manicled,<note place="margin">Art. &amp; Mon ex Regeſt. Longlandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> againſt whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other articles this was one, <hi>That in the yeare of our Lord,</hi> 1528. <hi>He was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and accuſed, to Cutb. then Biſh. of London, for affirming &amp; holding certaine articles contrarie to the holy Church, and ſpeciallie that all land and praiſe ſhould be giuen to God alone, and not to Saintes or creatures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No doubt if <hi>S. Paul</hi> had been brought before Biſhop <hi>Longland</hi> and his fellowes, he ſhould haue had the rewarde of an <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticke,</hi> for ſaying <hi>vnto the king everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>immortall, inviſible, vnto God only wiſe, be honour and glory for ever &amp; euer.</hi> The like hee hath alſo in another place;<note place="margin">1. Ti. 15.16. .6</note> but eſpeciallie for teaching ſuch doctrin, or rather ſuch <hi>hereſie</hi> (in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.<note place="margin">Heb. 13.15.</note>) <hi>Let vs therfore by him (Chriſt) of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſacrifice of praiſe alwaies to God.</hi> Jf praiſe muſt alwaies be offered to God, what time ſhall wee haue to offer that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to <hi>Saints?</hi> And yet the Apoſtle is not alone in this <hi>hereſie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 4.9. Re. 5.11.12</note> but the 4. <hi>Beaſtes</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> alſo, yea and the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7293:39"/> thouſands of Angels (becauſe <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> like ſo wel of multitude) giue <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>praiſe,</hi> and <hi>power, to him that ſitteth vpon the throne &amp; to the Lambe.</hi> And the 24. elders yeeld this reaſon why they alſo did rhe like, <hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, glorie, honour and power, For thou haſt created all things.</hi> Now becauſe wee cannot truelie ſaie ſo of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> it ſeemeth they by that reaſon will conclude, that <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Creatures</hi> muſt not haue that ſacred honour &amp; praiſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed vnto them. So that their ſong of thankſgiuing, is quite contrarie to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> &amp; verie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to that which Papiſtes call <hi>hereſie.</hi> Now if the Profeſſours of the truth, haue beene bloodily perſecuted by <hi>Papiſts</hi> for hearing onlie, or reading the <hi>VVorde of Truth</hi> for their inſtruction: why ſhould <hi>Recuſants</hi> thinke their Puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate <hi>Recuſancie</hi> ſo hard a matter?</p>
            <p>But <hi>Recuſants</hi> beſides that they are E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to our <hi>profeſsion</hi> and <hi>faith;</hi> are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo dangerous ſubiects, moe waies then
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7293:40"/> one, as before I ſaid. <hi>Firſt</hi> in that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine, yea and thinke it needfull vnder colour of perfourming the exerciſes of their <hi>Religion,</hi> that they ſhoulde haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſuch, as when occaſion ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, muſt put them in minde of their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to that <hi>Prophane VVretch,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they tearme moſt <hi>Holie Father,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by withdraw them from the kings obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Then</hi> alſo in that they take him to be the <hi>head</hi> of their <hi>Church,</hi> and ſo haue their harts bent on him, howſoeuer their bodie and goods, are for a time liable to the Princes will. And yet alſo they can finde meanes to make a ſtate of all they poſſeſſe, to defraude his Maieſtie of his right: &amp; can finde ſuch as would be loath to be accompted bad ſubiects, who can be content to be vſed as cloakes &amp; ſkon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in theſe their treacherous ſhifts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Recuſancie</hi> onlie then, how little ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Petitioner</hi> maketh reckoning thereof, is cauſe ſufficient to make them indure <hi>diſgraces, loſses,</hi> &amp; <hi>impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</hi> with ſuch other <hi>penalties</hi> as law impoſeth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7293:40"/> though as before I haue ſaid, verie few in compariſon of rhe number of <hi>Recuſants,</hi> are ſo dealte with all I ſay the abſtaining from our Churches (J meane in the time of <hi>diuine Seruice</hi>) vvhich is properly to be accompted <hi>recuſancy,</hi> importeth a fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther matter, as namelie becauſe they wil not be of our Church, that therfore they are of ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e other. And if of anie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> which hath for many hundred of yeares bin a Schole &amp; nurſery, of treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and treacheries of poiſonings, &amp; murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, of diſobedience and Rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and al ſuch dangerous attempts againſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Commonwealths.</p>
            <p>The caſe then ſtanding thus, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his <hi>Maiesties</hi> ſubiects are ſtolen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the inchaunting and ſugred ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, of the <hi>Romiſh Syrenes;</hi> I would ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it vvere vviſe <hi>Policie,</hi> but I am ſure it were good <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> to cauſe the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to <hi>ſweare</hi> not to <hi>Supremacie</hi> of our <hi>Gracious Soveraigne</hi> onlie, (a thing in theſe daies verie needful) but to the main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Rligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> too. A thing not ſtrang
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:7293:41"/> or voide of example of former times For <hi>Aſa</hi> &amp; the <hi>people</hi> with him,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 15.12.</note> 
               <hi>made a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to ſeeke the Lord God of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with al their hart, and with al their ſoule;</hi>
               <note place="margin">13.</note> 
               <hi>and that who ſoeuer wil not ſeeke the Lord God of Iſrael ſhalbe ſlaine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were ſmal or great, man or woema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> And they ſware vnto the Lord with a loud voice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">14.</note> 
               <hi>and with ſhouting, and with trumpets, and with cornets.</hi> We ſee here an oath ſollemnlie taken for the Seruice of God, wherby the People thought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues more ſtraitlie bound to performe the ſame. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Eſdra</hi> would reforme the tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them that had marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtrange wiues (as our <hi>Recuſants</hi> are wedded to the Italian head) he <hi>cauſed the cheife preiſts, and Levits, and all Iſraell, to ſweare that they would doe according to this word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ezra. i0. 5</note> (of putting away their ſtrang wiues) <hi>ſo they ſwore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea it ſeemeth the ſelfe ſame <hi>othe</hi> was put in practiſe in his Maieſties Realme of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral band.</note> 
               <hi>Ann<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> (as J take it) 1588. by a <hi>generall band,</hi> wherin, <hi>in the preſence of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:7293:41"/> Almighty god, and with his Maiesties au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorizing and allowance, the Nobles and other</hi> that ſubſcribed to the ſame, <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully promiſed and ſolemnly ſwore, like as</hi> (ſay they) <hi>hereby we faithfully and ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſweare and promiſe to take ane true, cafauld and plaine part with his Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is our ſelues, for averting of the apearand danger, threatned to the ſaid Religion &amp;c.</hi> So that we may vnderſtand hereby, that examples of the godlie prac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe of Zealous Kings, both old and new, may teach vs this godlie and Chriſtian policie, to prouide as wel as we can, for the continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Gods truth among vs: vvhich if we would in deuour as did <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiah,</hi> no doubt god ſhal bleſſ our atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts as he did his. <hi>In all the workes that hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan for the ſeruice of the houſe of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chro. 31 21.</note> 
               <hi>both in the Law &amp; in the coma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to ſeeke his God; he did it with al his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; proſpered.</hi> For as God loueth <hi>a cheerfull giuer,</hi> ſo he beſt accepteth obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that is done with <hi>cheerfulnes</hi> &amp; <hi>courage;</hi> not this faint ſeruice, or ſuch as is done with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:7293:42"/> vnwillingnes and grudging.</p>
            <p>In the former examples of <hi>Aſa</hi> and <hi>Ezra,</hi> we ſee alſo, that there was a <hi>Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> made for the Service of God, beſids the <hi>oathe</hi> that they tooke. Agreeable vvherevnto was (in my iudgment) not onlie that <hi>General band</hi> before mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed wherin very many in <hi>Scotland</hi> bound the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to defend the <hi>Religion</hi> profeſſed then, and now alſo within that Countrie: but alſo that <hi>Subſcription</hi> to a <hi>confeſsion of the faith,</hi> whervnto the <hi>Kings Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> &amp; al his <hi>Houſhold</hi> did ſubſcribe; which <hi>ſubſcription</hi> alſo, is vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſufficient penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie commanded vnto al <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that they ſhovld require the ſame of their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochians,</hi> and with all diligence and ſpeed to certifie the Refuſers of ſuch <hi>ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> as may appeare by the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>faith,</hi> and his Maieſties charge concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, <hi>Ano</hi>. 1580, Which courſes if they were taken vvithin his Maieſties domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with ſome execution of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt the obſtinate; J nothing doubt, but a great number would leaue Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7293:42"/> and would vvith hart and mouth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt the ſame, &amp; with their hand alſo (that might be an abiding witnes) ſhew their miſlike.</p>
            <p>And why ſhoulde <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelues miſlike of ſuch a courſe, ſeeing they alſo do practiſe the ſame? The <hi>leaguers</hi> in their <hi>Aſſociation</hi> doe ſweare, to reſtore Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to the forme of the <hi>Catholicke Rom: Church,</hi> as appeareth in a booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,<note place="margin">In Henry 3</note> 
               <hi>An historicall collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the moſt memorable accidents and tragicall maſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres of France;</hi> where alſo is to bee ſeene, that <hi>Henry the third</hi> the <hi>French king,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting an order of the <hi>holy Ghost</hi> bound them by ſolemne <hi>oath</hi> to ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions, as onlie pleaſed <hi>Catholike</hi> mindes, <hi>Anno</hi> 1579. Nay the late king of <hi>Spaine</hi> ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that all his haires and ſucceſſours in the Eſtate of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> ſhall for euer vpon their entrie into thoſe <hi>Signio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> take an <hi>oath</hi> for the maintenaunce of the <hi>Papacie</hi> &amp; that Religion; as is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a treatiſe latelie publiſhed, vnder the title of <hi>A relation of the religion vſed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:7293:43"/> in the weſt part of the worlde.</hi> And the <hi>Prince of Parma</hi> too, <hi>Governour</hi> for the ſaid <hi>Philip</hi> in the <hi>Low Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries,</hi> made the Cities ſubiect to his gouernment, <hi>ſweare</hi> to certaine <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſet forth by the appointment of <hi>Iohn Houchin Archb. of Machelen;</hi> which <hi>Articles</hi> being printed, <hi>Anno</hi> 1585. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſumme of that is taught in the <hi>Popiſh Church,</hi> both for the <hi>Pope, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery;</hi> which they did <hi>ſweare</hi> to maintaine euen to death, as much as in them ſhould lie, by councel or inſtruction. Shall this courſe then ſeeme ſtrange to anie, that hath ſo manie examples? Or can it bee thought vaine or needeleſſe, in theſe ſo da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous times? Shall we be leſſe zealous for the truth, then they for falſhood? Or ſhall they be found more circumſpect to maintaine ſuperſtition, and mens Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then wee for Gods true and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeruice, and the vndoubted <hi>written word?</hi> God forbid.</p>
            <p>O therefore that it woulde pleaſe our gracious God in mercie to looke vpon vs
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:7293:43"/> in moving his <hi>Maieſties</hi> Heart to vſe the ſelfe ſame meanes throughout al his Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minions, either to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell the back-ſliders vnto the true Service of God, or to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer ſuch falſe harts, as would make vs beleeue they build with vs, as did the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Beniamin, and ſeek the Lorde our God, as wee doe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 4.2.</note> though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they deſire nothing more, then to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh againe among vs the <hi>Popes</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and to bring into our <hi>Churches</hi> thoſe Popiſh abominations.</p>
            <p>Another cauſe of their <hi>vexations,</hi> ſaie they, <hi>is their conſtant perſevering in the religion received from their forefathers, as they from theirs.</hi> But that which the <hi>Petitioner</hi> tearmeth <hi>conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie,</hi> may much more aptlie be called <hi>wilfulnes</hi> or <hi>obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie.</hi> For I finde <hi>Conſtancie</hi> thus defined,<note place="margin">Iac. Hertel. de finit The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>olog.</note> that it is, <hi>Virtus, quae vera, iuſta, &amp; neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaria, conſtantèr, id eſt, eodem modo &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuò, dicit &amp; facit: a vertue that ſaith and doth the things that are true, iuſt, and neceſsarie, conſtantly, that is after one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and alwaies.</hi> It is therefore required
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:7293:44"/> that men ſhould firſt be ſure of the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Neceſsity</hi> of the things they hold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues firmely to beleeue the ſame. But for <hi>Popiſh</hi> doctrines, as it is certaine that manie of them beeing tried by the true Touchſtone of <hi>Gods VVorde,</hi> are found but Copper and counterfet: ſo ſundry points alſo, which they eſteeme as matters of great importaunce, are meere toies and trifles, fitter for fooles and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to ſport them withal, then for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to vſe in Gods ſeruice. I praie you then what conſtancie is in maintaining ſuch trumperie?</p>
            <p>That ſuch wilfulnes maie wel bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>obſtinacy,</hi> partlie in reſpect of the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine from whence it floweth, &amp; partlie in reſpect of the bad effect it worketh in <hi>Recuſants,</hi> maie eaſilie appeare. For fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence ſpringeth this ſtubbornes? Aſke <hi>S. Bernard</hi> he wil ſhew it.<note place="margin">Bernard. in cap. ieiuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſer. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Inde cordis duri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>indementis obſtinatio, quia meditatur quis non legem Domini, ſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priam volu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tatem. From hence commeth hardnes of hart, from hence ſpringeth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:7293:44"/> of minde, that a man doth not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate vpon Gods law, but on his owne will.</hi> How wel this painteth out the whole rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> I wold they had eies to ſee. For <hi>Gods worde</hi> is little reſpected among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but they are ſo wedded to their owne opinions, that hardlie wil they ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be diuorced from the ſame. And if you deſire to taſte of the bad fruit, that this corrupt tree yeeldeth,<note place="margin">Tertul. de paenit.</note> learne of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian. Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim timorem alia res quam contumacia ſubvertit,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>There is not anie other thing that overthroweth feare; then contumacie or ſtubbornes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee finde by experience this to bee moſt true. For <hi>obſtinacie</hi> maketh ſillie <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants,</hi> who are able to ſaie nothing at al in defence of their opinions, neither are acquainted with the verie <hi>Principles,</hi> no not of their owne Religion, (whereof to be ignorant, is a great ſhame for any that profeſſeth <hi>Chriſtianitie,</hi>) I ſaie their <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie</hi> is cauſe that they feare no Lawe, no Magiſtrate, no puniſhment, no perill of vtter deſtruction of bodie &amp; ſoule, but
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:7293:45"/> run on headlong to their own perdition, like men ſenſeleſſe, becauſe they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fearleſſe. Yea my ſelfe could name ſome, that being conferred withall, haue made ſo little reckoning of anie threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Gods wrath, againſt ſuch mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt contemners of his worde, as if they thought it a good ſport to goe to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, for companie of ſuch as they relie vpon.</p>
            <p>Another infallible note of their <hi>obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie</hi> is, that they wil not heare, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to conferre. If anie thing for their good and edifying be ſpoken vnto them, they ſtand mute much like their Images, that haue eares and heare not, mouthes and ſpeake not. And if with much a doe, you wring ſome words from them, their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon excuſe is, they are ignorant, they cannot reaſon: if I maie call it an excuſe, that is their greateſt accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Chriſt</hi> teachech vs, that ignorance is the cauſe of errour,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.29.</note> 
               <hi>You erre or are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, becauſe you knowe not the Scriptures, nor the power of God;</hi> they ſhould therby
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:7293:45"/> be made more deſirous to learne, if they will avoide errour: but they being ſettled, yea frozen in the lees of their ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, will not ſuffer themſelues to be reformed in anie wiſe, contenting themſelues with theſe ſtubborne anſwers, I am reſolued, I am ſatiſfied, my conſcience is perſwaded. As if God hauing commended vnto his Church the Miniſtery of his <hi>VVord</hi> as the onlie waigh-ſcales, and true <hi>Touchſtone</hi> of all <hi>Doctrins:</hi> and withall hauing giuen a generall charge to euerie member of of his Church <hi>to trie the ſpirites whether they be of God or not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.1.</note> becauſe there are as wel <hi>ſpirits</hi> of <hi>Errour,</hi> as of Truth: yet it ſhould be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted a high point of good <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> to receiue and ſtiflie to hold whatſoeuer their <hi>Popiſh Prieſtes</hi> ſhall ſaie vnto them, (for ſo they al teach, that <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualis à Nemine iudicatur</hi>) without any triall thereof, by waight or touch.</p>
            <p>But what is it wherein they perſevere ſo <hi>conſtantlie</hi> ſaie they, ſo ſtubbornlie ſaie I? <hi>In the religion they haue received from their forefathers, as they from theirs. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitentem
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:7293:46"/> habemus Reum.</hi> The <hi>Petitioner,</hi> in vttering his Griefe, confeſſeth his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; his owne mouth iudgeth him &amp; his fellowes; his owne words condemne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They haue their Religion from their <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> that is to ſaie, from men: we haue ours from God. For wee are ſaide to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>taught of God,</hi> not onlie in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of having Gods Spirit our inwarde Schoolemaſter to direct our harts, but alſo in regard that our Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <hi>by inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. i6.</note> as S. <hi>Paule</hi> teacheth <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy.</hi> Jt is therefore a ſufficient diſprofe of the Religion that <hi>Recuſants</hi> profeſſe, that it is receiued from their forefathers, as they receiued it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theirs, though the <hi>Petitioner</hi> bringeth it as an ornament &amp; beautie to Poperie, and a ſure argument of the truth thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 29.13.</note>
               <hi>Their feare towards mee</hi> (ſaith God by his Prophet Eſaie of the People of the Iews) <hi>is taught by the precepts of men.</hi> As if he ſaid; they worſhip and ſerue me, not as I haue commanded, but as men haue taught. Grievous is the accuſation wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:7293:46"/> God laieth to the charge of his people, that they followe the corruption of their <hi>fathers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 20.30.</note> 
               <hi>Are you not polluted</hi> (ſaith hee by his Prophet) <hi>with the customes of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp; commit you not whoredome after their abhominations?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15.3.</note> 
               <hi>VVhy tranſgreſſe you the commaundement of God, by your Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> ſaith our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> to the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſes?</hi> And becauſe it hath alwaies beene the faſhion of hypocrites to excuſe their Idolatries and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by that which their <hi>forefathers</hi> haue done before them: therefore God by his Prophet giueth this <hi>caveat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 20.18</note> 
               <hi>VValke not in the ordinances of your fathers, neither ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue their manners, nor defile your ſelues with their Idols.</hi> And the <hi>Apostle</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the <hi>Coloſsians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Beware least there bee any man that ſpoile you through Philoſophy and vaine deceipt, through the Traditions of Men.</hi> And <hi>S. Peter</hi> chargeth the <hi>Iewes</hi> with <hi>vaine converſation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>received by the Traditions of fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea in Matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> to hange vpon the doings or faith of <hi>forefathers,</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:7293:47"/> or of any <hi>men,</hi> is altogither vnlawfull and againſt Gods expreſſe commandement; <hi>VVhatſoever I command you, take heed you doe it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deuter. 12.30.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt put nothing thereto, or take ought there from.</hi> If then Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t muſt be obayed,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.2.</note> without tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the right hand, or to the left, as elſe where is ſaide without adding anie thing to it, or taking any thing from it, as here God by his ſervant <hi>Moſes</hi> chargeth; there is no libertie giuen to vs to followe our <hi>forefathers,</hi> but God only; who hath alſo appointed <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be our only Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.<note place="margin">Mar 23.8.10.</note> And therfore <hi>Tertullian</hi> that ancient writer moſt notablie teſtifieth, that no men may make choice what they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, no not the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelues might teach as they would,<note place="margin">Tert. ipraeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cript.</note> 
               <hi>ſed acceptam à Chriſto doctrinam fidelitèr nationibus annuntiarunt; That which they had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of Chriſt, they taught the people faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</hi> And then after teacheth vs howe to know the truth or true Religion, not by looking vnto our forefathers, but holding that which <hi>Eccleſia ab Apoſtolis, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoli
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:7293:47"/> a Chriſto, Chriſtus a Deo ſuſcepìt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>the Churches receiued from the Apoſtles, the Apoſtles from Chriſt, Chriſt from God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Godly therfore is the wiſh of <hi>Iuſtine</hi> the <hi>Martyr,</hi> more ancient then <hi>Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> For he liued not much more then 100.<note place="margin">Iuſt. Marc. colloq. cum Tryp. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeo.</note> yeares after Chriſt; <hi>Optarim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>candem mentem &amp; cateris, ne a ſeruatoris verbis diſcederent. Poſſunt enim religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem incutere, a via recta deflectentibus, &amp; meditantes ipſa, quiete reficere incun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimâ. I would wiſh that others alſo were of that mind that they would not depart from the words of our Sauiour. For they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worke Religion, in ſuch as turne from the right way, and refreſh with moſt ſweet reſt, ſuch as meditate therupon.</hi> And as he wiſheth that others would doe, ſo him ſelfe giueth example therin, inſomuch as <hi>Tryphon</hi> the <hi>Iew</hi> hauing experience ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of by the reaſoning which they had toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, thus ſpeaketh vnto him: <hi>Iam ante dixite ſemper Scripturis haerere quo ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das tutior: I haue ſaid before, that you all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſtick to the Scriptures, that you may
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:7293:48"/> walke more ſafly.</hi> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afterward he yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it as a reaſon why he will ſet downe their talk and conference in writing, <hi>Nec enim ſequor homines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuſtin. Mar. Ibi. poſt. me.</note> 
               <hi>aut doctrinas huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manas, ſed Deum, et quae ille docuit. For ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe I follow men, or the doctrines of men, but God &amp; that he teacheth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then vve ſee, that the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation that the <hi>Petitioner</hi> giueth vnto their <hi>Popiſh Religion,</hi> that they receiued it from their <hi>forefathers,</hi> is a ſufficient ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to reiect the ſame, vnleſſe they can fetch further the originall of it, then fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their forefathers, or their forefathers forefathers. And when they haue gon as farr as they can, to claime all Antiquitie of Man yet the <hi>Truth</hi> is that only, that cometh from <hi>God.</hi> If they therfore vvill perſwade vs, that their Religion is good, they muſt ſhew it out of <hi>Gods Booke;</hi> they muſt giue it this praiſe, that it is in <hi>Gods written word:</hi> which if they can, wee will rather beleeue one ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce rightly allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, according to the circumſtances of the place out of <hi>Scriptures:</hi> then all that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:7293:48"/> they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeake of their <hi>forefathers</hi> to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie generations. Herein we haue good warrant out of the ſacred <hi>word</hi> as I haue ſhewed; this was the practiſe of the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue</hi> Churches, as partlie is proued, &amp; maie verie plentifullie be confirmed.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt it be graunted vnto the Petitioner, that <hi>Recuſants</hi> indure ſuch <hi>vexations</hi> as they complaine of, onlie for their ancient Religion. For as there hath beene other cauſe of making both of the ancient and newer Lawes, againſt manie of the thinges wherewith they maie bee touched; ſo is ther other cauſe, why thoſe lawes ſhould be put in Execution: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to keepe vnder dangerous and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſubiects to the <hi>Eſtate.</hi> For euen that point of their Religion, whereby without anie good ground they ſubiect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the Pope, an vtter Enemie to al Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie in Princes, maketh them to be ſuch, as muſt carefully bee looked vnto. And yet that is not the Religion they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from their <hi>forefathers,</hi> and they from theirs, ſeeing it was neuer decreed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:7293:49"/> as a thing to be beleeued, in anie <hi>Councell</hi> before that of <hi>Florence,</hi> which was kept, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1439.</p>
            <p>We know alſo, as hath before beene ſaid, that they who are the dailie Plotters of all miſchieffes &amp; more then <hi>Pagan</hi> vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies againſt this flouriſhing Realme, (<hi>Ieſuits</hi> I meane &amp; <hi>Prieſtes,</hi>) are foſtered and maintained by <hi>Recuſants,</hi> yea ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored &amp; embraced by them, as that both their wil and their wealth is at their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing: and that they prepare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt their long looked for daie, that <hi>Cardinall Alen</hi> ſpake of (in a letter to a friend of his which is to be ſeene,) and diuers other ſince him,<note place="margin">VVeſton de tripl. ſtat. in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rorat.</note> doe inculcate, that vpon anie fit occaſion they maie ioine with them, in their miſchieuous attempts. That is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo confeſſed by one of the <hi>Scottiſh Ieſuits</hi> in a letter he writeth to the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> (as I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber for I haue not the booke now by me, but they are yet to be ſeene) wherin hauing reported what good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe they haue of their labours, he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alſo what they indevour, namely with
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:7293:49"/> Religion,<note place="margin">Diſcou. p. <hi>7. Anſw. to a Ieſuited Gent.</hi> Quodiib. <hi>2.</hi> art. <hi>7.</hi> Jnfanta's intertain. <hi>in the Engliſh Coll. at Val Iedolid.</hi> Jeſuit. cat. l. <hi>3.</hi> c <hi>16.</hi> Import. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. p. <hi>25.</hi> Reply to Parſ. li f. <hi>65</hi> Quodlib. <hi>6</hi> art. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> to plant in them an affection to the <hi>Catholicke king.</hi> And to that end doe they ſtill teach, that the <hi>Catholicke Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> &amp; the <hi>Catholike king</hi> are ſo linked, that <hi>one cannot take footing here vvithout the other;</hi> yea, that it is an <hi>Honourable Action to plant Religion here by Conqueſt.</hi> And though that ſmooth-tongued <hi>Traytor Ric. Southwell</hi> the <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> confeſſed from the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Medina's</hi> owne mouth, that ſo roome might bee made in <hi>England</hi> for the <hi>king Catholicke,</hi> little care would be had what became of other <hi>Catholicks:</hi> yet our <hi>Recuſants,</hi> rather then this <hi>Romiſh</hi> plot ſhoulde faile, will not only hazarde their owne eſtates and perſons here at home; but alſo ſend their Sonnes abroad to <hi>places purpoſely erected for our Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries Conqueſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Engl. Sem. at Siuil. val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. S Lucar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Quodlib. <hi>8.</hi> art. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> where they are ſure to proue <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiticall fire-brands,</hi> neuer to returne but to ruinate their <hi>Natiue ſoile.</hi> And muſt we yet thinke theſe men are only for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion vexed, who ſhew themſelues ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie waies, ſo dangerous ſubiects? No, no, as their Religion is <hi>not the plant that God</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15.13.</note>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:7293:50"/> 
               <hi>hath planted</hi> and therfore muſt be rooted vp, ſo are their doings ſuch as make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſtlie deſerue to be rooted out together vvith it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>complaint</hi> of this <hi>Petitioner</hi> being in ſome ſort conſidered of: it followeth alſo that we examine the Remedies which they ſay they haue vſed.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond part of the Petition.</note>VVhich (<hi>ſuppoſed</hi> vexations <hi>for Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>) moued vs before the end of the laſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, by our ſupplication deliuered to his Maieſtie, after declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our moſt dutifull alleageance, and proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that our Recuſancy proceeded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no other ground but feare to offend god: to offer (as before by a like ſupplication deliuered to our late deceaſed Queene in the <hi>27</hi> yeare of her raigne we had done) that if LL. Biſhops or other of ſingular note of learning among them at thoſe times ſhould be able to proue to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diuines of our Religion, that we be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of the Catholicke Romane faith, might without committing deadly ſinne repaire to their Churches, and be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:7293:50"/> there preſent at the exerciſing of your Religion (it being different from that we profeſſe) we would haue beene moſt ready &amp; willing to haue performed their deſiers therin</q>
            <p>This is the <hi>ſecond generall point</hi> hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this <hi>Petition,</hi> and toucheth the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies</hi> which the <hi>Recuſants</hi> haue (as hee ſaith) vſed, to eaſe them of their troubles. But the <hi>Petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er</hi> might haue dealt ſome what more plainely, if he had ſhewed all the waies they proued to ſhak of the yoke of their obedience; but indeed that Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration would haue deſerued litle fauour. For they haue vſed many moe waies the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are good, to effect this their deſire. They haue ſomtime burſt foorth into <hi>open Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions,</hi> as the ſtirres here in the <hi>North,</hi> the 11. yeare of her <hi>Maieſties</hi> raigne, that is now paſt all their practiſes, at reſt vvith god; and the ſundrie troubles of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land</hi> doe teſtifie. They haue had alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſecret purpoſes of <hi>poiſening,</hi> and <hi>murdering</hi> by any means they could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, the <hi>ſacred perſon</hi> of their <hi>Soueraigne</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:7293:51"/> not fearing Gods wrath, ether againſt murderers or againſt the diſpiſers of Gods ordinance.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ieſuit. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech.</hi> 3. c. 16.</note> J ſpeake not of the Invaſion, nor of that thriſe diabolical powder Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſon that was by them &amp; their Teachers procured, wherby they ſhewed that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would indanger the ſtate of the whole Realme, then not ſeeke to bring their purpoſes to paſſe; of which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts of France ſeemed to prophecy, vvhen they vvrit that the Ieſuites cared not <hi>to deſtroy a ſoule, a King, a paradice, the Church al at one blowe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jeſuit ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech.</hi> 1. 3. c. 13. &amp;c. 18.</note> 
               <hi>to make way to their Spaniſh and halfe paga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſigneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like their vnnaturall &amp; vnchriſtian plots and purpoſes, the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner</hi> had good reaſon to paſſe ouer vvith ſilence: and he maketh mention of that only, that without diſcredit he may ſpeake of, namely of ſome <hi>ſupplications,</hi> which he ſaith, they preferred both vnto our Late <hi>Gracious Queene of moſt happie memorie,</hi> and alſo to our <hi>moſt Renowned King,</hi> vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God in his great mercy hath giuen vnto vs. That which was deliuered
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:7293:51"/> (as he ſaith) to our Late <hi>Queene</hi> J never ſaw, nether (I thinke) haue hard of. But vnto the <hi>Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie</hi> that now raigneth (vvhoſe gouernment alſo the Lorde for his goodnes lengthen and proſper many yeares over vs) I haue ſeene ſundry, whether ſhould I call them <hi>Comminations or railing Libels;</hi> for ſome of them are noe other; and therfore <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications</hi> I cannot truely tearme them.</p>
            <p>But whatſoeuer they are, I meane not further to deale with them, then this <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition</hi> ſhall occaſion me. Our <hi>Petitioner</hi> complaineth afterwards that they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued no anſwere to the former <hi>ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Jf that to <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> were like vnto moſt of thoſe that J haue ſeene <hi>to his Maiestie</hi> (for foure haue come to my hands) they deſerued no fauorable an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. It is too ſaucie a part for ſubiects to pretend humble ſuit, and yet cloſly to threaten if their deſiers be not ſatiſfied; as doth the one eſpecially of their papers, by ſetting before his <hi>Maieſties</hi> eies, the departing of the <hi>Ten tribes</hi> from <hi>Rehobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:7293:52"/> his gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for that his anſwere to them was otherwiſe then they vvould haue it. And howſoeuer they vvill ſeeme to profeſſe more loyaltie, then they did ſhevv: yet is it harde truſting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their vvord, ſeeing manie deeds done by them of that faction, haue been dangerous and troubleſome to the ſtate, how ſmoothlie ſoeuer novv they ſpeake, that they may by that meanes ſpeed.</p>
            <p>And what good can they meane by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowing, that God approued that depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the <hi>Ten tribes</hi> for <hi>Rehobohams</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying their iuſt <hi>petitions,</hi> vnleſſe they meane to defend that <hi>Popiſh Paradox</hi> (&amp; doe thereafter too, if they be able) which is called by <hi>Sigebertus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sigebertꝰ in Chron. Ano Dom. <hi>1088.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Novella haereſis, a new hereſie; quòd malis Regibus nullam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant ſubiectionem, &amp; licet ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fidelitatis fecerint, nullam tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant fidelitatem, nec periuri dicantur, qui contra regem ſenſerint; imn ò qui regi pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruerit pro exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municato habeatur: qui co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra regem fecerit, à noxa iniuſtitiae &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurij abſolvatur;</hi> that is, <hi>That they owe no
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:7293:52"/> ſubiection or obedience to evill kings</hi> (and who are <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evill kings,</hi> muſt bee thought as it pleaſeth them to iudge) <hi>and though they haue ſworne to be faithful, yet owe they no obedience, neither are they to be called periured, if they bee againſt the king: but who ſo obeyeth the king is to be accompted for excommunicated: but who ſo is againſt him is abſolued from the fault of evill dealing or periurie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nether is this <hi>new haereſie,</hi> as he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it, an opinion of thoſe times onlie wherof he then wrot: but that <hi>hereſie</hi> is ſtil maintained in the <hi>Popiſh Church,</hi> as <hi>Ianſonius</hi> (no Enimie to <hi>Poperie,</hi> I warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you) telleth vs.<note place="margin">Mercur. Gal lib. <hi>2.</hi> Annꝰ <hi>1589.</hi>
               </note> For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>French King Henry the third,</hi> had for ſauing his owne life (or at leaſt his Crowne as the Preiſts confeſſe) killed the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> of <hi>Pariſe</hi> in a <hi>ſolemne Convocation</hi> did conclude,<note place="margin">Quod lib. <hi>9.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that the ſubiects were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from his obedience, and their oath, they might leuie mony againſt their King, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, beare armour and fight.</hi> And this their diueliſh <hi>Concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> they ſent to <hi>Rome</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:7293:53"/> to get it ratified. Much like vvas this <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anthon. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linet. li. <hi>2.</hi> Trag. Hiſt</note> vnto that which a <hi>Bacchelaur of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity</hi> maintained in <hi>Diſputation,</hi> ſome foure years before in the <hi>Colledge of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, That it was lawful for anie man, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat or otherwiſe, to depoſe or kil any kings or Princes, which were wicked, evill men, or heretickes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anthon. Colinet trag hiſt. li. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>True it is, that the <hi>Senate</hi> of <hi>Pariſe</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to ratifie the bloudie <hi>Concluſion</hi> of the <hi>Divines</hi> of <hi>Sorbone,</hi> &amp; required reſpit; but ſome ſeditious perſons by force took them, caſt them into priſon, choſe a new <hi>Councell.</hi> But how wel the <hi>Pope</hi> allowed thereof, maie appeare by the euent: for the <hi>king</hi> was murdered,<note place="margin">Quod lib. <hi>9.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> (by the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> practiſes, as <hi>VVatſon</hi> the <hi>Prieſt</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth) the <hi>Pope</hi> by a moſt blaſphemous ſpeech commended the fact, and in token of his good approbation thereof, that Beaſtlie wretch <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> was not aſhamed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare the <hi>Miraculouſnes</hi> of the <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> with the <hi>Incarnation</hi> and <hi>Reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and to affirme that that <hi>Spirit</hi> guided the <hi>king-killing Frier,</hi> that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:7293:53"/> guided the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ant. Colyn. trag. hiſt. li. <hi>7. Lib. intit De iuſta abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 3<hi rend="sup">1</hi>.</hi> Anno. <hi>1602</hi> Mark. <hi>7.</hi> Reply to Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons lib. An. to cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> But what will you more? He <hi>canonized</hi> for a Saint that bloudie Beaſt, and made him the <hi>God</hi> of the <hi>Pariſians.</hi> And for farther cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenancing of that <hi>holy murder,</hi> the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> ſet forth a diſcourſe, wherein they maintaine, that <hi>Any man might lawfullie kill a Tyrant</hi> (and ſuch muſt euerie one be reckoned who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they diſlike,) <hi>though there be neither ſentence of Church, or kingdome againſt him.</hi> Neither is this taught for good <hi>Popiſh Divinitie,</hi> in <hi>France</hi> onlie or <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo in <hi>His</hi> dominion, who is tearmed the <hi>Catholicke king,</hi> is this worſe then heathniſh leſſon, holden for ſound and good, as your <hi>Prieſts</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues aſſure vs. For in <hi>Salamanca</hi> it was concluded by the <hi>Profeſsours of Divinitie</hi> in that <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie,</hi> and the <hi>Preacher</hi> in the <hi>Colledge</hi> of the <hi>Society of Ieſus at Tire, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes in Ireland, might fauor the Earle of Tiron</hi> (when he was a <hi>Rebell</hi> and <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour) in his warres, &amp; that with great me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and hope of eternall rewarde, as though they warred againſt the Turkes.</hi> And that
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:7293:54"/> 
               <hi>al Catholicks ſinne mortallie, that take part with the Engliſh againſt Tyrone, and can neither bee ſaved, nor abſolved from their ſinnes by anie Prieſt, vnleſſe they repent &amp; leaue the Engliſh.</hi> Moreouer, <hi>They are in the ſame caſe that ſhall helpe the Engliſh with anie victuals, or any ſuch like thing.</hi> Laſtly, that <hi>the moſt worthy Prince Hugh O Neale and other Catholickes of Ireland, that fight againſt the Queene, are by no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction Rebels.</hi> I am not ignorant that the Prieſts charge the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> with this doctrine: but the <hi>Pope</hi> hath alſo confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the ſame as before is ſaid, &amp; therfore if ever opportunitie to execute the ſame would ſerue their turne,<note place="margin">Jmport: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. p. <hi>23. 24.</hi>
               </note> what <hi>Papiſtes</hi> hands would not be bloudie? Eſpeciallie ſince they are taught that in warrs for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> euerie <hi>Catholicke</hi> is bound to do as the <hi>Pope</hi> directeth without regarde to his Temporall Soveraigne:<note place="margin">Parſons Philopater. De iuſta ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat. H. <hi>3.</hi> Bannes in Thomam A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin. Quod lib. <hi>9.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and that though they may make ſhewe of obedience for a time yet as ſoone as they can get ſtrength to make a part, they may and ought put downe an Hereticall king.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:7293:54"/>
            <p>To this moſt impious, deteſtable, &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <hi>Hereſie</hi> theſe hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble <hi>Supplicatours</hi> (as they would be thought) ſing their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> as I take it, in ſaying, that departing from <hi>Roboam</hi> his gouernment by the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, was by the approbation of God as it ſeemeth.</hi> As if their departing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their lawfull king, could be liked of God. But <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> bringeth this among others as an example vvhereby hee will proue Gods iuſt iudgement in puniſhing ſin by ſinne, not Gods approuing the fact.<note place="margin">De gra. &amp;. lib. Arbit. cap. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Yet theſe men that defend ſuch daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous pointes of doctrine, in another <hi>Supplication,</hi> goe about to perſwade his <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> that they are the <hi>true &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubiects</hi> who obey for <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſake:</hi> they (I ſaie) who are at the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him, that is a plague to all <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> they who haue alreadie ſundrie waies tainted their credit, and ſhewed their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience; not content to intreat for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelus, pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (as vntruly, as boldly) that <hi>Protesta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, only for moral honeſtie of life, or inſtinct of nature, or for feare of ſome
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:7293:55"/> ſome te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall puniſhment, doe pretend true obedience.</hi> As if we, who are better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the duety we owe vnto <hi>the powers that are ordained of God,</hi> out of <hi>Gods Booke,</hi> by farre then they are, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie his authority who taketh vpon him to commaunde the <hi>Mightieſt Monarches</hi> vpon earth, acknowledging our <hi>Gracious King</hi> within his Dominions, to bee <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Governour</hi> vnder God; can be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſo vndutifull, as they that neither bee acquainted with thoſe <hi>ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> &amp; are deuoted to that <hi>Romiſh Prieſt</hi> and beleeue &amp; acknowledge his <hi>ſupreme power</hi> to commande.</p>
            <p>I vvil not ſpeake how leavvdly they ſeeke to diſhonour and diſgrace as much as they dare <hi>the ſacred Maieſtie</hi> of our <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>moſt honorable Senate</hi> of ſage <hi>counſellers,</hi> in making reſemblance betwene him &amp; <hi>Roboam,</hi> vnleſſe he yeeld to their requeſts, &amp; betwene his <hi>Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> moſt vviſe <hi>Councell,</hi> and the <hi>youths,</hi> whoſe adviſe <hi>Salomons ſonne</hi> followed. Nether will I ſpeake of the multitudes or
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:7293:55"/> manie thouſands that they ſpeake of to be of their minde as if therby they would make his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> afraid to deny that, which ſo manie requeſt at his hands. But in charging his <hi>Maiesties</hi> meeke &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful gouernment vvith crueltie as they doe, they ſhew themſelues to be of that crue,<note place="margin">2. Pe. 2.10. Iude. 8.</note> 
               <hi>that feareth not to ſpeak evil of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are in dignitie, but deſpiſe gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Theſe and many ſuch Reaſons maie be alleadged, whie their <hi>Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> might not ſeeme worthie to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvered but buried rather in ſilence.</p>
            <p>But to returne to the words of our <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner</hi> he ſaith that in the former <hi>ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation</hi> they <hi>haue proteſted, that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſancy proceeded from no other ground but feare to offend God.</hi> The <hi>ground</hi> wee confeſſe to bee good, if the cauſe of <hi>feare</hi> be iuſt; otherwiſe not. And I praie you what cauſe is there of beeing affraide to offend God by comming to our <hi>ſervice?</hi> Will he be offended if he <hi>onlie</hi> be praied vnto, as in our <hi>Churches</hi> we vſe to doe? I trow not; He hath giuen vs that comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:7293:56"/> he will not be angrie if we obey it.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> calleth him <hi>a hearer of praiers; Thou hearer of praiers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 65.2.</note> 
               <hi>to thee ſhall all fleſh come,</hi> which property becauſe we cannot ſaie it can belong to anie but God, wee therefore dare not pray to anie, but to him. And that which I haue ſaid of praier and &amp; crauing of ſuch things as we ſtand in need of at Gods hands, is alſo to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of <hi>Giving thanks</hi> for the things we receiue.<note place="margin">Iac. 1.17.</note> For ſeeing <hi>Everie good gift commeth from him,</hi> wee acknowledge our ſelues beholding to him for the ſame, and thanke him for it.</p>
            <p>We haue the <hi>Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> adminiſtred ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Chriſts</hi> inſtitution, which we haue iuſtified againſt your learnedeſt <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines,</hi> &amp; are ſtil ready to do. The reſt of our <hi>Service</hi> is nothing elſe, but that which your ſelues will confeſſe to be the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> In all this there is no ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe of <hi>feare,</hi> vvhy God ſhould bee <hi>offended,</hi> but rather vvell pleaſed. But indeed iuſt cauſe you haue to <hi>feare</hi> his heavy wrath, becauſe of your abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:7293:56"/> 
               <hi>Idolatries</hi> and <hi>Superstitions,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you pollute the name of God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file his worſhip.</p>
            <p>The ſubſtance of their former <hi>Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> which hee ſpeaketh of, ſtandeth vpon two Points, a <hi>Suite,</hi> and a <hi>Promis.</hi> The former is vttered thus, <hi>that the LL. Biſhops, or other of ſingular note of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhould proue to their learned divines, that Romiſh Catholicks might reſort to our churches, and be preſent at the exerciſe of our Religion, it being different from that they profeſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here <hi>firſt</hi> I woulde aſke the Queſtion, why their Requeſt was, that their <hi>learned Divines</hi> ſhould haue this proued to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? It behoueth euery one of you to bee ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for your owne ſelues and perſwaded in your owne conſciences,<note place="margin">2. Habac. 4.</note> 
               <hi>For the iuſt ſhall liue by his owne</hi> (not an other mans) <hi>faith.</hi> And you <hi>Recuſants,</hi> muſt anſwere (not your <hi>Prieſts</hi> for you) for your diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the <hi>Lawes</hi> that you ſhewe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and man.<note place="margin">Reply to the Apol. c. 6.</note> Yea &amp; a reply made by a <hi>Prieſt</hi> to a <hi>Libell</hi> called <hi>a breefe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie,</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:7293:57"/> ſheweth that ſundry <hi>learned men</hi> of the <hi>Popiſh Religion,</hi> haue beene of that minde, that <hi>Recuſants</hi> might come to our Churches;<note place="margin">So did Fa. Langdole alſo. Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. p. 97. 98</note> And that <hi>Boſgraue</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Jeſuite refuſed not our Churches, but came to them. Why then is it now required that your <hi>learned Divines</hi> ſhould be taught that leſſon, which long ſince they had learned?</p>
            <p>Jt was (ſaie the <hi>Prieſts</hi>) ſometime <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> but it is nowe made <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it <hi>is a ſigne diſtinctiue,</hi> whereby a Catholicke is knowne from one who is no Catholicke. Well, then there is in our <hi>Seruice</hi> nothing that maketh it vnlawful, there is not in our <hi>Churches,</hi> to make <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants</hi> abſtaine from them. All the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is, that <hi>Papiſts</hi> muſt be knowne to bee <hi>Papiſts,</hi> &amp; their not going to the <hi>Church</hi> is this <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue,</hi> whereby they are knowne; in ſo much as the <hi>writer</hi> of the Replie,<note place="margin">Repl. to the Libel. c. 6.</note> in the <hi>chapter</hi> and place afore na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſaith thus, <hi>it was ſomewhat more to be lamented percha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> (ſpeaking of <hi>Papiſts</hi> comming to <hi>church) then to be blamed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:7293:57"/> it became to be a ſigne distinctiue.</hi> And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he addeth, <hi>For this conſideration only, in the iudgment of the Ieſuits in their Rom. Colledge, made the going to Church, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus may our <hi>Petitioner</hi> ſee that their <hi>Learned Divines</hi> agree in this point, that if it had not beene the <hi>ſigne distinctiue</hi> to know a <hi>Romiſh Catholicke</hi> from a <hi>True Chriſtian,</hi> they mighte haue come to Church. Now if I ſhould aſke of our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of this new learning, where they did learne in <hi>Gods Booke,</hi> that this <hi>ſigne distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue</hi> is a thing ſo neceſſary, that in regard therof it is required that a Subiect ſhould breake his <hi>Princes</hi> godlie <hi>Lawes,</hi> &amp; ſuch as commaunde preſence at ſuch <hi>Seruice,</hi> as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues cannot finde anie fault with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; it would I ſuppoſe trouble both <hi>Ieſuits</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> to make a direct anſwere. For the Apoſtles of our Saviour Chriſt, though the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> were aboliſhed, and therefore the <hi>Iewes Service</hi> &amp; <hi>Rites</hi> not to be vſed of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> yet came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their <hi>Synagogues,</hi> and ſo could not but
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:7293:58"/> be preſent at their Seruice.</p>
            <p>And yet their difference in <hi>Religion</hi> was ſuch, as that S. <hi>Paule</hi> writeth to the <hi>Galatians</hi> plainely,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>If you be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing;</hi>
               <note place="margin">4.</note> 
               <hi>Yee are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed from Chriſt, who ſoever are iuſtified by the law, yee are fallen from grace.</hi> But notwithſtanding this diverſitie of <hi>Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> that was now betweene <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> it was not made a <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue,</hi> whereby a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſhould bee knowne, that hee might not reſorte to their <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Art. 13. 13. 14</note> No one the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie, <hi>Paule &amp; they who were with him, entered into the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue</hi> (of the <hi>Iewes) on the Sabbath day, &amp; ſate downe.</hi> Neither did the <hi>Iewes</hi> knowe anie ſuch <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">15.</note> but after the <hi>lecture</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Prophets, The Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Synagogue ſent vnto them ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yee men and bretheren, if you haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny word of exhortation for the people, ſay on.</hi> Now if <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> were not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to obſtaine from <hi>Iewiſh Synagogues,</hi> where ſuch were as held a <hi>Religion</hi> that would quite depriue them of the <hi>Grace
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:7293:58"/> of Chriſt:</hi> I truſt our <hi>Recuſants</hi> haue noe cauſe of feare to come to our <hi>Churches,</hi> where themſelues confeſſe that in our <hi>Service</hi> is nothing but good, and godly.</p>
            <p>Nether was there any <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue</hi> that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were bound to vſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſhould be knowne from <hi>Pagans,</hi> or from <hi>Heretickes</hi> ſuch as were the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> &amp; others. For this is eaſie to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, in that they had at <hi>Rome</hi> their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret <hi>Conventicles,</hi> and ſome of <hi>Nero</hi> his <hi>Court</hi> reſorted to them, but they kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues as much as they could vnknowne, becauſe they knewe that being detected, they ſhould be cruelly dealt withal. They therfore neuer ſo much as dreamed vpon anie <hi>ſigne distinctiue,</hi> but rather deſtered to appeare like other men, ſauing only in ſuch things, as were aginſt the true <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God.</hi> And <hi>Catholicke</hi> and <hi>Orthodoxe Christians,</hi> in the time of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> vvere faine to hide themſelues in Caues and corners, as themſelues confeſſe, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be vnknowne rather then knowne.</p>
            <p>And why doe theſe <hi>Phariſes</hi> J meane
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:7293:59"/> 
               <hi>Ieſuits</hi> and <hi>Priests,</hi> lay ſuch burdens vpon the <hi>Laie Recuſants,</hi> as themſelues will not touch vvith their little finger? They diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe themſelues in their apparel, and vſe what meanes they can, not to be diſcouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed for ſuch as they are. Whie ſhould ther not be aſwel a <hi>ſigne distinctiue</hi> of the <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> as of the <hi>Profeſsion?</hi> It ſeemeth <hi>Preiſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuits</hi> are wel content, the <hi>Lay Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants</hi> ſhould ſhew themſelues in the fore front, and they wil take part vvith him that ſaid <hi>Ego cro poſt principia.</hi> For hee knevv the end of the fraie, was the ſafeſt part therof.</p>
            <p>Againe if it be lawfull for <hi>Ieſuits</hi> and <hi>Preiſtes</hi> in their <hi>Scholes</hi> to appointe what ſhalbe a <hi>Signe diſtinctiue,</hi> whie maie not rather our <hi>King</hi> &amp; the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>Realme</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> command that <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſhal come, the <hi>Men</hi> with ſhauen crownes, the <hi>woeman</hi> couered with <hi>vayles</hi> like to <hi>Nunnes,</hi> or al of them with ſome other badge or Marke into our <hi>Churches,</hi> that therby they might be knowne what they are. Wil they then come, if there may be
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:7293:59"/> ſuch a <hi>Signe diſtinctiue?</hi> Jt were not amiſſe they were proued whether they would or not.</p>
            <p>And I am verilie perſwaded, that if ſuch order ſhould be taken, their <hi>Romiſh Teachers</hi> would finde out ſome other new cauſe, why they ſhould not come at our <hi>Churches.</hi> For it is not (if truth were know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en) a <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue</hi> that they ſo much regard, as <hi>a ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d rete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiue,</hi> wherby they may be holden in their blindnes ſtill. It is <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams</hi> policie, that maketh the <hi>blind guids</hi> of our <hi>Recuſants,</hi> keep their followeres from our <hi>Churches,</hi> of whom the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> thus teſtifieth.<note place="margin">1. Kings 12.26.27.</note> 
               <hi>And Ieroboam thought in his hart, now ſhall the kingdome returne to the houſe of David, if this people goe vp and doe ſacrifice, in the houſe of the Lorde at Ieruſalem, then ſhal the hart of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple turne againe to their Lord, even to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam king of Iudah.</hi> And therfore, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter followeth in the ſtorie, the <hi>King</hi> by ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viſe of his <hi>Councel,</hi> made and ſet vp <hi>Calues</hi> at <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and got <hi>Preiſts,</hi> fit for the purpoſe, and ſo kept them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:7293:60"/> to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to worſhip there.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pope</hi> &amp; <hi>Popiſh diuines</hi> knowe, that if <hi>Recuſants</hi> might haue free libertie to come to our <hi>Churches,</hi> they would ſoone growe into miſlike of their ſuperſtitious toyes, and groſſe <hi>Idolatries,</hi> howſoeuer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe through their intiſing wordes, are for a time holden in ignorance, and miſlik not <hi>poperie.</hi> And for that cauſe they dare not ſomuch as permit their <hi>Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre with <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> forfeare leaſt in the end, they leauing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould make choice of the vndoubted <hi>Truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reply to a li. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> For euen <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> the <hi>Preiſts</hi> hold as vnlawful, as re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pairing to our <hi>Churches</hi> for ought I ſee.</p>
            <p>Thus then I reaſon, to ſatiſfie in ſome part the <hi>Requeſt</hi> of the <hi>Suppliants</hi> heare me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned: The <hi>Popiſh divines</hi> are reſolued that comming to our <hi>Churches</hi> is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, but only that it is now accompted a <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue,</hi> to knowe a <hi>Papiſts</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <hi>Protestant:</hi> but other <hi>ſignes diſtinctiue</hi> may be deviſed beſids that, therfore it is not neceſſary that that <hi>ſigne</hi> ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and ſo by conſequent it may bee
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:7293:60"/> left. Nay ſeeing it is but the <hi>ſigne diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> that they ſtand vpon, and other <hi>ſignes</hi> of <hi>diſtinction</hi> may be vſed, leſſe repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to our <hi>Godly lawes,</hi> and wherby Papiſts ſhal not be found, ſo diſobedient Subiects as now they are: I therfore may be bold to affirme, that if <hi>Recuſants Teachers</hi> had that loialtie to their <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient affection to the <hi>Sate,</hi> that here they doe and elſwhere they will pretend; they would teach them a new leſſon, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwad them, that vſing ſome other <hi>ſigne,</hi> in this they ſhould not be Rebellious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and man. For the more offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue that they are (eſpecially to the <hi>Powers ordained of God</hi>) the more they ſinne, and the greater ſhalbe their condemnation.</p>
            <p>Againe wheras <hi>ſignes diſtinctiue</hi> are but <hi>Accidentall</hi> and belong not to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Subſtance</hi> of our <hi>Religion,</hi> as in this point in queſtion is plaine, ſeeing that it is by <hi>learned diuines</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g <hi>Papiſts</hi> reſolued that once <hi>Papiſts</hi> might lawfullie haue come to our <hi>Churches,</hi> vntil ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made their not coming, a <hi>ſigne</hi> to knowe a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:7293:61"/> by, I may therof thus reaſon; No <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſigne</hi> or obſeruation muſt make vs leaue <hi>neceſſarie duties,</hi> that belong to the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of our obedience, but the <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue,</hi> is ſuch an externall obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, therfore for it we muſt not leaue ſuch <hi>neceſſarie duties,</hi> as belonge to the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of our obedience: and by conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the <hi>Kings Maieſties Lawes</hi> are not for it to be broken.</p>
            <p>The firſt two <hi>Arguments</hi> are ſo gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the verie words of the <hi>Preiſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> and ſo grounded vpon good reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agreeable to the <hi>word</hi> that I hope I need not proue them. In this <hi>Third Argument,</hi> the <hi>Maior</hi> is confirmed by that which God commanded <hi>Samuel</hi> to ſay to <hi>Saul,</hi> when he had broken Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22.</note> in ſparing <hi>Agag</hi> King of <hi>Ameleck</hi> and ſome of the beſt of their cattle, <hi>to obey is better then Sacrifice, and to harken, is better then the fatt of Rammes. I deſired mercy &amp; not Sacrifice,</hi> ſaith God by his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Hoſea &amp; the knowledg of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>is more then burnt offerings.</hi> If that externall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:7293:61"/> that God commaunded, be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded in reſpect of <hi>obedience:</hi> what ſhall we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaie of this <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue,</hi> which ſome <hi>Politicke</hi> heade of a Popiſh <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> hath found out?</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Minor</hi> Propoſition, which is that <hi>Recuſants</hi> not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches is ſuch an <hi>external</hi> obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their fellowes maie know them to bee <hi>Papiſtes,</hi> that which I haue alleadged out of the <hi>Reply to the Libel,</hi> teacheth vs to be true, and for that cauſe they call it a <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe; The hearing of the Word, &amp; Receiving of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> is not to be omitted for any <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue,</hi> as the Example of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe and his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> who entred into the <hi>Ievviſh Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues,</hi> though they were Enemies to the doctrine that <hi>Chriſt</hi> &amp; his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> taught, maie ſufficiently confirme vnto vs. And yet our <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> neither ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor do ſay, that our doctrine, eſpecially in our <hi>Booke of Common Praier,</hi> is more faultie then theirs was: nay they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe therin no fault
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:7293:62"/> to bee found: therefore much better may <hi>Papiſts</hi> reſort to our <hi>Churche,</hi> without in curring any danger of deadlie ſinne. For what deadly ſinne can be ſo much as ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be, in comming to the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es where there is <hi>firſt, Confeſſion</hi> of our ſinnes, <hi>Prayer</hi> vnto God for forgiuenes &amp; other his Graces, <hi>Thankes giuing</hi> for his benefits, <hi>Hearing</hi> of the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing</hi> of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and ſuch like Godly excerſcies?</p>
            <p>But for the better ſatiſfaction of the <hi>Petitioner</hi> his demaund, I would haue the <hi>Learned diuines</hi> of the <hi>Popiſh Sect,</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the Reaſons that <hi>M. Bell</hi> a Papiſt, alleadged in a certaine <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> wherin he defendeth it to be lawful for <hi>Recuſants</hi> to reſort to the exerciſes of our <hi>Religion</hi> ſo it be with <hi>proteſtation.</hi> By which reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s it ſeemed the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> were perſwaded to ſet downe their <hi>Reſolution</hi> before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, <hi>that onlie</hi> (marke <hi>only) the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ſigne distinctiue,</hi> made <hi>Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull. And becauſe the <hi>Reply</hi> to the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:7293:62"/> ſeemeth to bee of that minde too, as I haue ſhewed, therefore having ſpoken ſomewhat to that, I thinke it needleſſe to goe through the <hi>nine Reaſons</hi> that <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> bringeth,<note place="margin">Martin of Schiſme.</note> or the <hi>nineteenth</hi> that <hi>Greg. Martin</hi> hath, wherby they would proue their comming to our Churches vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full partly becauſe in ſo ſhort a diſcourſe as this is, it cannot bee perfourmed, but chieflie becauſe it ſeemeth that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being better examined, that <hi>ſigne</hi> of <hi>diſtinction</hi> is in their opinions the onlie let. But that being but a deviſe of Man to haue ſuch difference, is not ſufficient to diſcharge anie <hi>Subiect</hi> of their <hi>Obedience</hi> to their <hi>Soveraigne</hi> and his <hi>Lawes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God.</p>
            <p>Now ſomewhat having beene ſpoken concerning their <hi>Petition</hi> to anſwere it: their promiſe was, <hi>to haue beene more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and willing to haue performed</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Suppliants) their deſires therein,</hi> that is, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to our churches. Which promis how eaſily it may bee perfourmed out of that which hath bin ſaid, may be gathred.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:7293:63"/> For we call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to <hi>Idolatrous ſervice,</hi> or anie ſuperſtitious or will-worſhip: we know to come to ſuch, it is vtterly vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. We wil them not to heare a tongue that they know not, a language that they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not, as in <hi>Popiſh Churches</hi> they doe. But they are by <hi>Law</hi> commaunded, and therefore in things ſo lawful and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, their obedience is of dutie required, they are commanded (I ſaie) to come to Churches, where God <hi>onlie</hi> is ſerued, &amp; to hear his <hi>word</hi> in ſuch a tongue, as they that will heare may alſo learne ſuch due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as God requireth of them. The <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner</hi> thus goeth forward.</p>
            <q>And for that vvee received none an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to either of the ſaid petitions, the defect whereof as we are in charitie to thinke, proceeded in regarde of the LL. Biſhops then being, nor your LL. were not made acquainted therewith: vve now deemed it very behoofefull, yea ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for vs, to tender and proſtrate the ſame offer to your LL. most humblie beſeeching your Honours, that wee may
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:7293:63"/> receiue ſome ſatiſfying anſwere there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, from your LL.</q>
            <p>The <hi>Petitioner</hi> not finding the former <hi>Supplications</hi> to haue that effect that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants</hi> deſired, now tendereth this <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> eſpeciallie vnto ſuch as are of chiefe place, &amp; beſt accompt among the <hi>Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> And as he doth charitably interpret, the not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving anſwere of the <hi>former Requeſts:</hi> ſo doth he alſo in my iudgment demand but that which is reaſonable in his Suit, if it were not that hee requireth a <hi>ſatiſfying anſwere,</hi> in that matter, that hath beene ſpoken to ſo oft, &amp; ſo fully, that it is much to be doubted, that they who cannot bee <hi>ſatiſfied</hi> with that which hath alreadie beene ſet downe, wil not thinke anie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere a fit <hi>ſatiſfaction</hi> to their demands. But yet becauſe they aſſure vs of their yeelding to our deſires, which is in effect nothing els, but that they would <hi>bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to be reconciled vnto God,</hi> as <hi>Paule</hi> writeth to the <hi>Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10</note> for wee ſeeke not theirs, but them: therfore wil J inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:7293:64"/> to performe what they requeſt. And thus it followeth.</p>
            <q>Aſsuring you, that if it may be proved in manner as is before mentioned, that we may goe to any ſuch Church without committing deadly ſinne; or that which wee doe nowe profeſse, is not the ſame which we receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our forefathers, &amp; that which they received fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theirs ſucceſsiuelie, ever ſince the converſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this countrie to Chriſtianitie, that wee will then bee readie to ſatiſfie your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires therein.</q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third part.</note>Wee are nowe come to that which in the beginning I ſaid, was the <hi>third</hi> &amp; laſt part of this <hi>Petition</hi> which is the Requeſt it ſelfe. But this hath ſundrie branches. For <hi>firſt</hi> the demand is vttered by way of <hi>condition,</hi> with promiſe of performing our deſires, if the <hi>Requeſt</hi> be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But vpon a ſecret <hi>ſuppoſall,</hi> that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done that is required, they woulde hope not to be proſecuted by <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Cenſures,</hi> but rather that our <hi>BB.</hi> ſhoulde bee meanes to <hi>His Maieſtie</hi> for
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:7293:64"/> them, or elſe they aſſure vs it will much incourage their followers as in that which followeth in the <hi>Petition,</hi> they profeſſe.</p>
            <p>Now then to come to the <hi>Conditions</hi> here <hi>firſt</hi> propoſed; they are two. The <hi>firſt</hi> is this: <hi>If</hi> (ſay they) <hi>it may be proued in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as is before mentioned, that we may goe to any ſuch Church, without committing deadly ſinne:</hi> Concerning this their <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> I ſuppoſe I haue already ſpoken ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, conſidering that the <hi>Reply</hi> to the <hi>Libell</hi> called <hi>a breife Apologie,</hi> written by a <hi>Preiſt,</hi> very latelie (for it was printed <hi>Anꝰ.</hi> 1063.) ſaith in plaine words (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue alleadged) <hi>that Catholicks co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Church was ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what more to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented perchance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reply. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>then to be blamed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was a ſigne diſtinctiue.</hi> Now that it is not needfull that there ſhould be any ſuch <hi>diſtinction,</hi> or if any ſhould be, yet that anie other rather then this may ſerue that turne, yea that this being ſo offenſiue as it is, may not be vſed, J haue already touched al theſe points.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort <hi>Bells diſcourſe,</hi> and the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:7293:65"/> determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> tend al to that end too. So that this point J will ſhut vp with this one <hi>Argument.</hi> That which is agreed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be lawfull, by conſent of their <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Diuines</hi> on their ſide, ſauing in reſpect of a thing that may eaſily, yea muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be altered, they maie doe without committing deadlie ſinne: Bur <hi>Recuſants</hi> comming to Church is ſuch as is lawfull, but o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in reſpect of that <hi>diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> which they ſuppoſe ſhould by this meanes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, which maie and muſt be altered: therfore their comming to our Churches maie wel be vvithout deadlie ſinne. The <hi>Maior</hi> cannot be denied; But for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderſtanding of the <hi>Minor propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> it muſt be ſomwhat vnfolded.</p>
            <p>The <hi>diſtinctiue ſigne</hi> that is hetherto ſpoken of, is ether to be taken, in reſpect of <hi>Recuſants</hi> themſelues, as that one of them may by it knowe another, in which ſence J haue hitherto ſpoken of it: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this taking of a <hi>diſtinctiue ſigne,</hi> my <hi>Minor</hi> is ſufficiently proued before, in that ſuch <hi>ſignes</hi> are not needfull, nether
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:7293:65"/> haue beene vſed in the time of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> yea they are manie waies offenſiue, &amp; for that cauſe to be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Or elſe, the <hi>diſtinctiue ſigne</hi> is to bee vnderſtood, as that we therby knowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be <hi>Romiſh Catholicks.</hi> If in this ſence they ſpeake of a <hi>diſtinctiue ſigne,</hi> then J giue them to vnderſtand, that this <hi>ſigne</hi> we truſt not. For the <hi>Preiſts</hi> tell vs in the <hi>Reply to a breife Apologie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reply. cap. <hi>17.</hi> &amp; <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> that the <hi>Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its</hi> taught that leſſon in <hi>Scotland</hi> (wee doubt not alſo but in <hi>England</hi> too) <hi>that a man might lock vp his conſcience, after he had hard maſſe, and then goe to the Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants Churches,</hi> which we ſuppoſe too manie doe beleiue and practiſe; wherof alſo commeth that name of <hi>Church Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</hi> Therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to our <hi>Churches,</hi> is not a <hi>ſigne</hi> wherby wee eſteeme them that ſoe doe, to be <hi>Recuſants.</hi> Since ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by that <hi>ſigne</hi> wee doe not knowe al <hi>Papiſts;</hi> no, nether yet <hi>Papiſts</hi> only ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from our <hi>Churches,</hi> but ſundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo, who haue as little agreement with <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as <hi>Papiſts</hi> haue with the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:7293:66"/> 
               <hi>Truth</hi> that is not a true <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue</hi> betwene <hi>Romiſh Catholicks,</hi> and <hi>profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> whervpon your <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diuines</hi> conclude, your going to our churches not to be vnlawful or vngodly.</p>
            <p>What is performed for the <hi>firſt condi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion</hi> let the indifferent Reader iudge. The <hi>ſecond</hi> followeth: <hi>Or</hi> (if it be proued that) <hi>that which we now profeſſe,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is not the ſame which we Receiued from our forefathers, and that which they receiued from theirs ſucceſsiuely, euer ſince the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this countrie to Chriſtianitie &amp;c.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the <hi>Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> wherby the <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tioner</hi> ſuppoſeth he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth their <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> becauſe they receiued it from their <hi>forefathers,</hi> I haue before ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But here he goeth ſomewhat further, challenging this doctrine that nowe they haue in the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> to haue conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and come to them <hi>ſucceſſiuely,</hi> from the <hi>firſt converſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of this <hi>Country</hi> to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity:</hi> or as the former <hi>Petition</hi> to his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> ſaith, from the <hi>Converſion</hi> of <hi>Donaldus,</hi> which was king of the <hi>Scotts,</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:7293:66"/> and became a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> about the <hi>yeare</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 203.</p>
            <p>And hath the <hi>Romiſh Religion</hi> that now is, wherein we diſſent from them ſo great <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt time that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> receiued <hi>Chriſtianitie?</hi> No; neither yet from the time of <hi>Donaldus,</hi> who came to the knowledge of Chriſt, more then a hundred yeares after this parte of this <hi>Ile</hi> of <hi>Brittaine</hi> did. For though many of our <hi>Chronicles,</hi> report, <hi>Lucius,</hi> who raigned over vs about the yeare of our <hi>Lord,</hi> 156. firſt to haue receiued <hi>Christianitie</hi> into this <hi>Iland:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſ. Bar.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 1. <hi>p.</hi> 286.</note> yet <hi>Barronius</hi> (whom I hope our <hi>Petitioner</hi> will truſt,) telleth vs that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Aramathia</hi> who begged the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of <hi>Chriſt</hi> &amp; buried it, came hither out of <hi>France,</hi> and planted the Goſpel, being ſent by <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Patricij Hib epiſt. Caeſ. Baro. tom. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>286.</hi> Doroth. Synopſ.</note> of whoſe pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Goſpell</hi> about <hi>Glaſcenburie,</hi> there are manie teſtimonies approued by <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> themſelues.</p>
            <p>Yea there are that affirme, that <hi>Simon Zelotes</hi> came hether, and here was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; and that <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> of whom S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:7293:67"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romanes</hi> maketh mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Niceph. Theod. Soph.</note> was <hi>Epiſcopus Britanniae factus, made Biſhop of Britaine.</hi> Yea there be alſo, &amp; they ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ancient, that write that <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Paule</hi> preached here; ſo that it cannot be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, but our <hi>Converſion</hi> vnto <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> was in the time of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And hath <hi>Romiſh Religion</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued from them ſucceſſiuely? Jt will not proue ſo.</p>
            <p>To goe through al the doctrine which they profeſſe, were a matter of greater la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour then is requiſite; &amp; yet becauſe the <hi>Petitioner</hi> ſo faithfullie doeth aſſure vs, that if ether the one, or the other of theſe maie be proued by vs, they wil bee ready to yeeld to our deſire in comming to the Church; as I haue alreadie aſſaide to doe the one of the thinges they require: ſo doubt I nothing, but that I ſhall ſatiſfie the other part of their demande, and ſo binde them as by a double bond, to doe as they promiſe. And that the matter may be more plaine, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the meaneſt of that ſort, I purpoſe only to ſpeak of thoſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:7293:67"/> pointes, which are chieflie required of them.</p>
            <p>And <hi>firſt</hi> of the verie props that <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> ſtandeth on, and the feete whereby it creepeth forward: that is, the <hi>Supremacie,</hi> and <hi>Traditions.</hi> It is a doctrine which <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Catholicks</hi> do hold moſt firmely, that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>ſupreame head</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> yea if we will giue any credit to <hi>Boniface</hi> the <hi>eighth Pope</hi> of that name,<note place="margin">Extra. de Maior &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient. vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>It is neceſsarie to ſalvation to beleeue, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie creature is ſubiect to the Biſhop of Rome.</hi> But how will it bee proued, that they, or any of them that planted <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie</hi> in this Realme, taught anie ſuch thing, that it might come from them ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiuelie? It is certaine the <hi>Apostles</hi> knewe no ſuch <hi>Supremacie</hi> belonging to <hi>Peter.</hi> For if they had, it being ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to ſaluation, as <hi>Pope Good-face</hi> telleth vs, they had beene vnfaithful <hi>Stewards</hi> in not deliuering that doctrine: yea by their doings they teach vs there vvas no ſuch thing. For the <hi>Apostles</hi> hearing that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> had receiued the <hi>VVord</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:7293:68"/> careful to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confirmed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,<note place="margin">Act. 8.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſent vnto them Peter &amp; Iohn.</hi> If he had knowne himſelfe to haue beene <hi>ſupreame head</hi> ouer them, he would haue directed them, they ſhould not haue appointed him to goe.</p>
            <p>And did <hi>not Paul withſtand him to his face,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he was to be blamed?</hi> It would be thought a ſawcie part for anie body to do ſo to the <hi>Pope</hi> now. But let any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> look with an indifferent eie throughout the whole <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and he ſhal neuer finde anie ſuch Authoritie granted vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> from whom they would perſwade the world that they haue this ſupremacy. I know there are ſome places wreſted to ſerue that turne, which alſo are ſo fullie anſwered in ſundrie learned bookes, that all the <hi>Papists</hi> in the world, will neuer be able out of them to proue, the <hi>Romiſh Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car</hi> to be <hi>Supreame Head</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> I therefore will but point vnto that, which the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the purer Age of the <hi>Church</hi> thought hereof, wherby we maie truely gather, whether they thought this
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:7293:68"/> 
               <hi>ſuperiority</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> to haue any good ground in Gods book or not. Howſoeuer <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> more boldlie then truelie doth pronounce,<note place="margin">De Rom. Pontif. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eſt revera non ſimplex error, ſed pernitioſa haereſis, nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re B. Petri primatum a Chriſto inſtitutum: It is</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Cardinall) in deed no ſimple errour, but a pernitious hereſie, to deny that the Supremacie of S. Peter, was inſtituted by Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was then the 6.<note place="margin">Conc. Carth <hi>6.</hi> capit. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Carthage</hi> an <hi>Hereticall Councell,</hi> or did they holde a <hi>pernicious hereſie,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they decreed that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> ſhould haue their proper priuiledges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to them, as well as the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> had his? <hi>Fauſtinus,</hi> &amp; others whom <hi>Boniface</hi> 1. ſent thither for him, did what they coulde by alleadging falſe <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> to haue reſerued a <hi>ſuperioritie</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> but they coulde not preuaile. Neither coulde the <hi>Popes</hi> beſt friends then ſaie, that either <hi>Chriſt</hi> had giuen him ſuch preeminence, or the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> had taught it, but onlie they allead<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:7293:69"/> a falſe <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Councell,</hi> to haue deceiued the world withall, as the ſtory of that <hi>Councell</hi> ſheweth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Preamb. Concil. Chal.</note>And when <hi>Valentinian</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> and <hi>Placidia</hi> alſo &amp; <hi>Endoxia Empereſſes,</hi> wrote to <hi>Theodoſius</hi> that a <hi>Councell</hi> might be aſſembled within <hi>Italie,</hi> being moued thereto by <hi>Leo</hi> himſelfe (then <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>) as is there confeſſed; and they were diſpoſed to ſpeak as much as they could, for credit of that <hi>See,</hi> yet all they could write was, that <hi>to him principatum Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotij ſuper omnes, antiquitas contulit. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie beſtowed vpon the Biſhop of Rome, to be chiefe over Priests.</hi> They therefore intreated, <hi>vt locum habeat &amp; facultatem, de fide &amp; Sacerdotibus iudicare: that hee might haue place and power, to iudge of the faith, and of Prieſts.</hi> A verie vnequall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, made as it ſeemeth by the inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Leo</hi> himſelfe, perchance preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the errors that were in manie of the <hi>Eaſterne</hi> Churches, and the ſoundneſſe which yet the <hi>Rom.</hi> Church retained, as partlie alſo appeareth he did.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:7293:69"/>
            <p>But the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> vvhich was the <hi>fourth Generall Councel,</hi> ſmelling out the purpoſe of <hi>Leo</hi> as it ſeemeth, did plainelie decree that the <hi>Archbiſh.</hi> of <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople</hi> ſhould haue as good priviledge as had the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Chal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced. Act. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> And doe <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſinus</hi> the <hi>Popes Legate</hi> what he could, by alleadging again, a <hi>falſe Canon</hi> of the <hi>Nicene Councell, Quòd Eccleſia Romana ſemper habuit primatum, that the Church of Rome, hath alwaies had the ſupremacie,</hi> (ſo you ſee, forgerie &amp; falſe dealing hath bin an old practiſe of the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi>) yet the <hi>Councell</hi> would needes ſo decree, crying with one conſent, <hi>Haec iusta ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia, haec omnes dicimus, haec omnibus placent, haec omnes dicimus, hoc iustum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretum, Quae conſtituta ſunt valeant: It is a iuſt ſentence, we all ſaie thus; we are all pleaſed with this: we all ſay thus. It is a good decree, As it is ſaid, ſo let it ſtande.</hi> And thus is it plaine enough, that ſince nether <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> and they who were ioined with him as <hi>Legates</hi> in the <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel</hi> of <hi>Carthage;</hi> neither <hi>Paſchaſinus</hi> and his <hi>Aſſociates</hi> in
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:7293:70"/> the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> neither the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour</hi> &amp; <hi>Empereſses</hi> in their <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at <hi>Leo</hi> his owne Requeſt, and by like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhoode vpon his <hi>Information;</hi> neither laſtlie the 630. <hi>Biſhops</hi> in that <hi>Councell</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, could once alleadge any <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> for the <hi>Popes</hi> Superioritie, but that the <hi>Councell</hi> decreed againſt the ſame; it is (I ſaie) manifeſt, that for 455. <hi>yeares</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> which nowe they wring to prooue the ſame, were not ſuppoſed to avowe the <hi>Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that <hi>Succeſsion</hi> of this <hi>Doctrine</hi> wil never be brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> of this Land to <hi>Chriſtianitie:</hi> no there was no ſuch doctrine for many hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeares after <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But in deede the <hi>firſt</hi> ground of that <hi>doctrine</hi> muſt be ſoughte for, in the time of <hi>Phocas</hi> that <hi>Cruell Murderer,</hi> who (as before I ſaide) becauſe by ſo euill meanes hee came to the <hi>Empire,</hi> that hee might with more approbation keepe his place, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to gratifie <hi>Boniface Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:7293:70"/> with an vnwonted, but not vndeſired ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: <hi>Magnâ contentione</hi> (ſaith Platina) <hi>obtinuit à Phoca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plat. in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifac. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vt haberetur &amp; dicere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ab omnibus, Romana Eccleſia, caput om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Eccleſiarum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Palmerius.</note> An addition vnto <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius his Cronicle</hi> ſaith, <hi>Id conſentient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Phoca inſtitutum eſse: that with much a doe</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Platina) Boniface the third obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of Phocas, that the Church of Rome, ſhould be accompted and called, the head of all Churches,</hi> and as <hi>Palmerius</hi> in his <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> ſaith, <hi>Phocas was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent that ſhould be ordained.</hi> And another ſtorie ſaith that <hi>Phocas firſt obtaie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Benevenuti. Auguſtal. in Phoca.</note> (marke <hi>firſt obtained</hi>) this title to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that now, ſomewhat more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 600 yeares after <hi>Christ</hi> began the Claime to this <hi>Title</hi> to be ſomewhat worth, if the vniuſt honor, giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by a <hi>bloudy Vſurper</hi> of the <hi>Empire,</hi> may make a good claime. But notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding all that <hi>Phocas</hi> his decree could prevaile, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Conſtantin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ople,</hi> and the <hi>Patriarches</hi> alſo of <hi>Raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> and ſundrie others, yea all the <hi>Greeke church</hi> held out, nether wold acknowledg
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:7293:71"/> anie ſuch <hi>Supremacie</hi> in the <hi>Pope,</hi> though it coſt ſome of them ful deare,<note place="margin">Pla. in Leo <hi>2</hi>
               </note> &amp; namely the <hi>Patriarche</hi> of <hi>Ravenna.</hi> In the ende commeth <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. in honeſtie much like the <hi>firſt fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der</hi> of the <hi>Papacie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Extra de Maior. &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. vnam ſanctam.</note> 
               <hi>Phocas,</hi> and he laieth the <hi>ſecond</hi> ſtone of this fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, making it as before you hard, a matter <hi>neceſſarie to ſalvation</hi> to beleeue this ſo euill a proued Article.</p>
            <p>And yet for al this the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> thought their ambitious Title not well grounded, nether that men would for all <hi>Pope Boniface</hi> his decree, that came al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 1300. yeares after Chriſt, beleeue the <hi>Pope</hi> to be ſuch a one: therfore in the <hi>Councel of Florence</hi> about ſome 8. or. 9. ſcore yeares ſince, they got it and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch <hi>ſubſtantiall</hi> and ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pieces of doctrine,<note place="margin">Bartho. Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranza ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma concil.</note> ratified and confirmed, in theſe words, <hi>Definimus ſanctam Apoſtolicam ſedem, &amp; Romanum pontificem, in vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum orbem tenere primatum.</hi> Thus nowe ſome 1400. yeares after our <hi>Converſion</hi> to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> is this principall point of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> come to that
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:7293:71"/> honour, to be accompted a doctrine to be beleeued, For vntil the Councell had decreed it, it might not properly haue that credit. I truſt then, it appeareth to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie indifferent iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that this <hi>first</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which our <hi>Recuſants</hi> hold, wanteth at the leaſt 1400. yeares, of the conſent of the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> it ſelfe, of that ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which our <hi>Recuſants</hi> imagine it hath.</p>
            <p>The <hi>other Propp</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> is the doctrine of <hi>Traditions,</hi> which that wicked conventicle at <hi>Trent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Seſs. <hi>4</hi> decret. de Script. cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> is not aſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make equal to the vndoubted <hi>worde of God, Traditiones ipſas, tum ad fidem, tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admores pertinentes tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vel ore tenùs a Chriſto, vel a ſpiritu ſancto dictatas, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuâ ſucceſſione in Eccleſia Catholica ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uatas, pari pietatis affectu ac reverentia ſuſcipit &amp; veneratur.</hi> This <hi>councel</hi> ſay they <hi>with like honour and affection, doth receiue and reverence euen the Traditions aſwell belonging to faith, as to manners, as if they had beene pronounced from Chriſts owne mouth, or from the holy Ghoſt. A de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> ſubiect to that reprofe of our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:7293:72"/> Chriſt, why doe ye tranſgreſse the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15.3.</note> 
               <hi>by your traditions?</hi> For in verie manie things, <hi>doth the Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> expreſlie againſt Gods written word, vnder colour of thoſe <hi>vnwritten verities,</hi> as they falſlie tearme them, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none I truſt it ſhall appeare by the indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Reader.</p>
            <p>But here my purpoſe is only to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether Traditions be a fit Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to try our doctrines by, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie, whether we haue receiued this Rule or Trial of our <hi>Religion, ſucceſſiuely</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Apostels</hi> or not? But the matter is plaine, though the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſometime na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth <hi>Traditions,</hi> yet hath he noe meaning to deliuer vs anie <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>faith,</hi> or leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon belonging to our ſaluation, but onlie ſuch as are contained in the <hi>writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word.</hi> For this cauſe the <hi>Apoſtle to Timothy</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it <hi>depoſitum</hi> more then once,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that is, a <hi>thing committed,</hi> and already deliuered, that we ſhould not looke daielie for newe Tradition therof. And <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iude</hi> ſpeaketh therof much to the purpoſe, exhorting
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:7293:72"/> thus <hi>ſtriue earneſtly for the ſaith once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude. 3.</note> meaning that our <hi>Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> is not like vnto <hi>mens lawes,</hi> which muſt alwaies, as inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces are eſpied, be reformed: but <hi>once</hi> it is deliuered, and that which already we haue receiued, we muſt not change.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Keepe</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Paul) the true patterne of the wholſome words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tm. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>which thou haſt hard of me.</hi> So that we ſee they had a <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne</hi> from which they might not ſwarue. And neceſſarie it was ſo to be, that they might the better obſerue the Exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame <hi>Apostle</hi> elſwhere, who would not haue vs <hi>henceforth any more as Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren caried about,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>and wauering with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry winde of doctrine,</hi> which in noe wiſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be avoided, if <hi>Traditions</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Touchſtone.</hi> But as in the matter of <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie,</hi> ſo in this alſo let vs ſee what the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers</hi> did when any queſtion of <hi>Religion</hi> was to be deſcuſſed. For therby ſhal it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto vs, whether they iudge the <hi>Scriptures</hi> or <hi>Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> the fitteſt meane to trie our <hi>Religion</hi> by. Nether doe I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:7293:73"/> here to trouble the Reader with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite numbers of Sente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, which might be gathered out of the <hi>Fathers</hi> touching this point. For there is not anie thinge ſo common in them, as <hi>Teach this out of the Goſpels and the writings of the Apoſtles; or proue this out of the law, the Prophets, and the Euangeliſts and Apoſtels writings.</hi> J ſaie nothing more common in ſundry of them, then theſe or ſuch like ſentences.</p>
            <p>I therfore purpoſe but to point to ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e generall thinges which in their practiſe for this matter may be obſerued, whervp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on maie be inferred, that the <hi>Fathers</hi> did not ſo vnderſtand that which in the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> may be read of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which they haue deliuered, as if it were meant of any ſecret doctrines, or other leſſons then are ſet downe in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For by <hi>Scriptures</hi> eſpecially did they diſproue hereſies,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Apoc. Hom. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> as all ſtories plainelie teach. <hi>Occiduntur haereſes per Catholicos</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine) cum in ſcripturarum testimonijs opprimuntur. Hereſies are kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Catholicks, when they are ouerlaied
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:7293:73"/> with teſtimonies of Scriptures.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodoret hiſt. li. <hi>1.</hi> cap <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doret</hi> in one <hi>Chap.</hi> recordeth twice, howe <hi>Euſeb.</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> and other <hi>Arrians</hi> were <hi>by the Scriptures</hi> confuted. But this is in the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories</hi> and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> ſo plaine &amp; commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it is needleſſe to bring many proofes therof. I wil therfore conclude with that notable Teſtimonie of S. <hi>Auguſtine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in epi. Joh. tract. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra inſidioſos errores, Dominus voluit po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerefundamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Scripturis: The Lorde woulde lay in the Scriptures a foundation or ground worke, againſt deceitfull er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as in priuate writings, <hi>Hereſies</hi> were by <hi>Scriptures,</hi> not by Traditions beſides the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> confuted: ſo in <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels</hi> too. Jn the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodoret. li. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> ther was a charge giuen by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> and good <hi>Emperour,</hi> that they ſhould determine &amp; debate ſuch matters, as ſhould be in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie among them, <hi>literarum diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùs inſpiratarum teſtimonijs: by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Scriptures giuen by inſpiration;</hi> which he immediatly before called the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:7293:74"/> 
               <hi>Bookes</hi> of the <hi>Evangeliſts, Apoſtles, and Prophets. S. Auguſtine</hi> being deſierous that a good end ſhould be made, and a quiet order taken, between the <hi>Catholicks</hi> and the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> writeth to a <hi>Biſhop</hi> of their <hi>Sect</hi> called <hi>Fortunius,</hi> requiring that ſome peaceable courſe maie be thought vpon, and ſome indifferent place apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note place="margin">Auguſt. epiſt <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> where they may haue a <hi>councel or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> but with this condition, <hi>Faciamus Codices Canonicos praeſto eſſe, let vs take or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the bookes of Canonical Scriptures be there ready,</hi> much like is that which is reported of <hi>Meletius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Samb. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nop. per Cralb.</note> between whom &amp; <hi>Pauling</hi> there was ſome queſtion, <hi>In ſede ponatur ſacrum Evangelium, et nos ex v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> parte ſedeamus: let the holy goſpel be laied vpon the ſeate, and let vs fit on ether ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things I haue breiflie touched, which ſundry others haue fully &amp; largly handled, that Recuſants may ſee, that the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the purer time, did not ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand theſe words of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſuch like,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> The, 2.15</note> 
               <hi>Stand faſt, and keep the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:7293:74"/> or traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which you haue bin taught ether by word or by our Epiſtle;</hi> as if he deliuered one thinge by writing and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother by worde of mouth: For they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge no other <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which in the <hi>writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worde</hi> is contained, and therfore doe they ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie vrge the Heretickes, to <hi>ſhew</hi> that they teach out of the <hi>writings of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Evangeliſts, and Apostles:</hi> Therby declaring, that the <hi>written word</hi> (for that onlie is to be ſaid that it maie be ſhewed wheras words not written are not ſeene but hard) maie be <hi>Iudge</hi> in matters of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> And therfore <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> calleth <hi>This word the waigh-ſcales of Truth</hi> verie aptlie, as alſo the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are even for this cauſe called <hi>Canonicall,</hi> becauſe they are the <hi>Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> or <hi>Rule</hi> according to which our <hi>life</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> muſt be framed.<note place="margin">Auguſt de bapt. contra Donat. lib. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feramus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſtateram canonicam de ſcripturis ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctis ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de the ſauris domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicis, &amp; in illis quid ſit grauius appe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>damus, imò non appendam us, ſed a domino appe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa recognoſcamus. Let vs bringe the Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:7293:75"/> waigh ſcale out of holy Scripture, as out of the Lords treaſure &amp;, let vs waighin the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what beareth waight: or rather let not vs waigh them, but acknowledge that, which the Lord hath waighed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Jn preſcript aduerſ. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</note>Indeed <hi>Tertullian</hi> maketh mention of certaine <hi>Heretickes</hi> that ſaide that <hi>Christ</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> deliuered not al their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine openlie, but ſome in ſecret, iuſt as now our Papiſts doe, but they haue that note of <hi>Heretickes</hi> for their labour, &amp; are written againſt both by him, and <hi>Irenei</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">Iren lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi> Jre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. li. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> who was before him. And <hi>Irenei</hi> chargeth the <hi>Carpocratians</hi> with that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie,</hi> and the <hi>Valentinians</hi> too. So that though the <hi>Fathers</hi> did not ſo vnderſtand thoſe words, <hi>keepe the Traditions, &amp;c.</hi> as doe the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> yet you ſee, who did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande them ſo, of whom I truſt you wil be aſhamed to be accompted follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſeeing that you ſeeme by your <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ſo deſirous to bee ſatiſfied for ſuch points. It appeareth by that which I haue ſaid, that not <hi>Traditions,</hi> but onlie the <hi>written word,</hi> muſt both decide al <hi>contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies</hi>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:7293:75"/> in <hi>Religion,</hi> and alſo be the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, wherevpon they muſt be built.</p>
            <p>Now that I may yeelde ſome Reaſon of that which before I ſaid, that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion they haue of the <hi>Popes Supremacy,</hi> and this their doctrine, that <hi>Traditions</hi> are of <hi>equall Authority</hi> with the <hi>vvritten word</hi> of God, are the verie <hi>props</hi> that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Popiſh Religion;</hi> you muſt confide, that when <hi>Fathers</hi> yea &amp; <hi>Scriptures</hi> too, are ſo plaine againſt them, that they can in no wiſe wreſt them to ſerue their turn, neither haue anie reaſonable colour of Anſwere, to ſuch Arguments as out of them are framed againſt Popery: then do they either flie to the <hi>Popes Authoritie</hi> &amp; <hi>Priviledge,</hi> to allow and Interpret what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is written; or to this orher ſhift of <hi>Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> wherby they would perſwade, that they haue it from the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and ſo they bring ſome ſhew of Truth, to that which is otherwiſe, &amp; indeed, moſt falſe.</p>
            <p>To ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery particular doctrine which is in the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> receiued, it were too tedious: Yet needfull it is that
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:7293:76"/> 
               <hi>Recuſants</hi> ſhould be ſatiſfied in this their Reaſonable Requeſt, whether the <hi>Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> that they profeſſe, haue beene from the <hi>Converſion</hi> of this <hi>Land</hi> or not. For per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance hereof, let them aſke of their <hi>learned Divines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">VVhitak. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crov <hi>1</hi> queſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> whether <hi>Maſter VVhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker</hi> hath trulie reported, out of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Peter a Soto</hi> a <hi>Papiſt</hi> of no ſmall reckoning, <hi>Caniſius, Lindan,</hi> and <hi>Pereſius,</hi> al great vpholders of the <hi>Popiſh Religion,</hi> of ſuch doctrines, as themſelues acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, they receiue from <hi>Tradition.</hi> For if he haue written truelie (as indeed hee hath) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>learnedst Divines</hi> that haue beene of the <hi>Papiſtes</hi> in our age, whoſe Bookes the <hi>Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Ieſuits</hi> now are not worthie to carrie, do confeſſe that which now our <hi>Recuſants</hi> profeſſe, almoſt in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie point, is grounded not vpon <hi>Gods word,</hi> but vpon <hi>Traditions,</hi> yea and ſome of them late too: and therefore not that faith, which was at the <hi>firſt converſion</hi> of this <hi>Countrie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Soto co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Brentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>Out of <hi>Peter a Soto</hi> he reckoneth theſe <hi>The offering of the ſacrifice of the Altar,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:7293:76"/> Invocation of Saints, praier for the dead, The ſupremacie of the Biſhop of Rome, hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of water in baptiſme; The whole Sacrament of Confirmation, Order, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie, pennance, annoyling, merit of workes, neceſsitie of ſatiſfaction, numbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our ſinnes to the Priest.</hi> Out of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſius</hi> he reckoneth theſe,<note place="margin">Caniſ. cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſ. cap. <hi>5.</hi> Lind. pan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. pl. li. <hi>4. c. 10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>worſhip of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, certaine times of fasting, lent, all that is in the Maſſe, praier and offering for the dead.</hi> Out of <hi>Lindane, that Peter was at Rome, and his ſupremacy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tabul.</hi> 6.</note> yea and the <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Sacraments</hi> too, are (ſaith hee) <hi>by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, conſecration of oile</hi> and <hi>water in baptiſme, reall preſence, Communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in one kinde, that the Euchariſt is a ſacrifice, that it muſt bee kept and worſhipped, private Maſſe, Confeſsion of ſinnes, ſatiſfaction, Indulgencies, Purgatory;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pereſ. par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And <hi>Pereſius</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that <hi>ſingle life of Prieſtes, is by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi> So that, if theſe <hi>Learned Divines</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay true, our <hi>Recuſants</hi> may eaſilie vnderſtand, that all their <hi>Religion</hi> is built, not vpon the <hi>Rocke</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> but vpon the <hi>Quick-ſand,</hi> of <hi>Mens Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:7293:77"/> and <hi>Inventions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea and <hi>Canus,</hi> who may wel be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned among the <hi>learnedſt Divines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Canus de trad. Aposto li. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>3.</hi> Fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dament. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Papiſts</hi> haue had in our times and our <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> daies too, confeſſeth <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fundamen</hi> 3</note> not to bee taught in <hi>Scriptures</hi> plainely: yea <hi>Invocation of Martyrs for helpe, celebrating of their memories, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Images, In the ſacrifice of the Euchariſt, that the Priests muſt make and receiue with the body the bloud alſo, that the Sacrament of Confirmation &amp; Orders are not to be reiterated;</hi> theſe things (ſaith he) and manie ſuch like, are neither <hi>plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> nor <hi>cloſely</hi> contained in <hi>Holy writ.</hi> But what ſtand I vpon this? <hi>Fiſher</hi> ſometime <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> well knowne to the <hi>Recuſants</hi> of our time, and accounted a <hi>learned Divine</hi> in his time: granteth <hi>that Purgatory</hi> and <hi>Indulgences,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aſsert. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. confut. Artic. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> are but of <hi>late</hi> found out.</p>
            <p>Now therfore I ſuppoſe our <hi>Recuſants Requeſt</hi> is <hi>ſatiſfied.</hi> Jt is plainely ſhewed, that wheras this our <hi>Realme</hi> was brought to the knowledge of the <hi>truth</hi> in the daies
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:7293:77"/> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> if not by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: yet all that ever the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> holdeth, is of <hi>Tradition,</hi> &amp; not out of the <hi>word of God:</hi> yea and for ſundrie points thereof very late too, as out of <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher</hi> I haue ſhewed for <hi>Purgatorie &amp; Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons,</hi> as for the number of 7. <hi>Sacraments,</hi> the <hi>Supremacie,</hi> yea and <hi>Purgatorie,</hi> they had their approbation but in the <hi>Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Councell,</hi> almoſt in our Fathers daies. But for thoſe other, that are fathered vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as manie of the reſt of the Popiſh opinions are: it is plaine enough that the <hi>Ancient Fathers</hi> in the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> and <hi>purer</hi> Age of the <hi>Church,</hi> neuer acknowledged anie ſuch for materiall points of <hi>Religion,</hi> which muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be beleeued, neither would receiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, but out of the <hi>written word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I graunt they vſe alſo often the name of <hi>Tradition;</hi> ſomtimes therby ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying, that which in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> is written for our learning and inſtruction, not mens Traditions or deviſes: And in this ſenſe it is commonlie vſed by <hi>Irenei</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:7293:78"/> and others:<note place="margin">Ire<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, li. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> as when he ſaith, <hi>ab Apoſtolis traditum eſt veritatis Evangeliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of truth is delivered from the Apoſtles.</hi> Now the <hi>Goſpel</hi> we know to bee written. Yea three times in one <hi>chap.</hi> he vſeth this word <hi>tradiderunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1</note> they <hi>delivered</hi> (from whence commeth the worde <hi>Tradition</hi>) ſpeaking of the writing of Gods worde. Somtime alſo they vſe it in the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is now moſt common, for <hi>vnwritten doctrines.</hi> This I note, that ſuch as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly would not be deceiued, may know that not everie place wherein anie of the <hi>Ancient Fathers</hi> name <hi>Tradition,</hi> muſt make for the <hi>Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> for which the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Church ſtriueth ſo earneſtlie, &amp; of which they make ſo great reckoning.</p>
            <p>But for the <hi>Recuſants</hi> ſake, thus I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: whatſoeuer doctrine was not taught and proued out of the <hi>written word,</hi> the <hi>Fathers</hi> for 4. or 5. hundred yeeres after <hi>Christ,</hi> did not receiue as the doctrine of the <hi>Church: But</hi> the doctrine the <hi>Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> now profeſſe, (as out of their <hi>learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> before is ſhewed,) is not prooved
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:7293:78"/> out of the <hi>Scriptures:</hi> therefore the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> for 4. or 5. hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeers after <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not allow it to be the doctrine of the <hi>Church;</hi> &amp; ſo it followeth that their <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers</hi> ſucceſſiuelie from the <hi>Converſion</hi> of this land, that is, from the <hi>Apostles</hi> times, haue not beene taughte that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>Wee nowe looke for performance of promiſe, whereby you haue aſſured vs, that either of the <hi>Conditions</hi> beeing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, as I truſt both are: you <hi>wilbe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to ſatiſfie our deſires in comming to Church.</hi> We would haue ſome hope that you would be as good as your word, but that your <hi>Blinde-guides,</hi> haue grauen (I thinke) with a pen of ſteele in your harts, a moſt ſottiſh &amp; Vnchriſtian perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that you muſt not ſee, but by their eies, nor heare, but by their ears; you muſt not know anie thing, but that they will haue you to know: and then bee you ſure you ſhall know nothing, that maie bring their credit into any queſtion, or their doctrine into anie triall. Well ſaid <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:7293:79"/> moſt truely, of the lawes that were made againſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and fitly it maie be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vnto the matter in queſtion, <hi>Suſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta lex eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. in A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>polog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>quae probari ſe non vult; impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba autem, ſi non probata, dominetur. The Law is to be ſuſpected, that will not ſuffer it ſelfe to be tried: but it is wicked, if not being tried it bear the ſway.</hi> For I am ſure, that no man woulde thinke hee meant to warrant his gold to be good, that woulde charge him that receiueth it, that in anie wiſe he muſt not try it, either by <hi>Scale</hi> or <hi>Touch.</hi> Yet <hi>Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</hi> in matters of <hi>Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> are content to truſt ſuch as will let them trie nothing.</p>
            <p>By this meanes, howſoeuer our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering of this or anie other <hi>Petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> may be of it ſelfe <hi>ſufficient,</hi> yet if they whome you take to be your <hi>Learned Diuines,</hi> ſaie it is not anſwered, you muſt truſt them, &amp; continue ſtil in Ignorance. And who can hope that they, that partlie vpon diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentednes, partlie vpon vaine intiſments, have entered by vndutiful diſloialtie, into great danger and diſfauour, wil leeſe you,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:7293:79"/> if by any meanes they maie hold you one their ſide, by whom only they are maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, in their vnſatiſfied humour. So that <hi>Recuſants</hi> are (J muſt needs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe) through their owne wilfulnes or follie, much to be pittied; becauſe they are not only lead aſide from the right way, but alſo are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be lead ſo by them, that will neuer let them returne into it againe. Therfore howſoeuer your <hi>Petition,</hi> maie be deemed <hi>reaſonable:</hi> yet I feare you ſhal finde alwais (if God would giue you eies to ſee it) your Preiſts dealing with you herein not vnreaſonably only, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo damnable.</p>
            <q>But if vpon ſuch mature diſcuſſion it ſhall appeare, that we can noe way goe to your Churches without incurring god his wrath, and the damnation of our ſelues; we hope that your LL, will the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forbeare to proſecute vs with any ſpirituall cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but rather mediate, in reſpects wel knowen to your ſelues, or reſtoring againe into his Maieſties fauour, and the mittigation of ſuch penalties and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:7293:80"/> vexations, as for our Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie are dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impoſed vpon vs.</q>
            <p>Vpon an abſurde <hi>Suppoſition,</hi> the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner</hi> frameth a twofold Requeſt, the <hi>one</hi> that our <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſhould not oppoſe themſelues againſt them by <hi>Cenſures Ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall;</hi> the <hi>other</hi> that they ſhould be meanes to procure his <hi>Maieſties</hi> fauour. But the <hi>Petitioner</hi> here offereth greate wronge to <hi>Biſhops, Preachers,</hi> &amp; <hi>Goſpellers</hi> to all whom his <hi>Petition</hi> is directed, in that he imagineth, that, they, who haue this 47. yeares, preached, taught &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the truth of the Goſpel, ſhould all this time neuer haue vſed mature diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame vntil now they ſhould be rouſzed, as it were out of a ſlumber, by this <hi>Remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer,</hi> wheras intruth every point of <hi>Poperie,</hi> hath ſo often beene diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed, and diſcuſſed too; in ſo many learned Treatiſes the impietie therof ſo diſcouered, that all that their <hi>Ieſuits and Preiſts</hi> can doe, can neuer couer &amp; hide the nakednes therof againe.</p>
            <p>Yea the more we vnfold the plaites of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:7293:80"/> 
               <hi>Poperie,</hi> the more cauſe we ſee to deteſt the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, &amp; to pray that our king and rulers ſhould haue a watchfull eie ouer the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorers thereof. For what is <hi>Poperie</hi> but a <hi>Religion</hi> pached vp of <hi>Mens</hi> Inventions, as is before ſhewed, a ſea of ſuperſtition &amp; Idolatries, of will-worſhips; a Religion contrarie to the word, that muſt be, and is the ground of <hi>True Religion:</hi> wherin trifles and toyes, are accompted as accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table worſhip of God; wherin <hi>God</hi> is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honored, by vndue honour giuen to the <hi>Creatures;</hi> A Religion that teacheth to diſobay <hi>Princes,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath ſet in the <hi>throne,</hi> to diſobay Magiſtrates and them that haue Authoritie, to poiſon, murder and kill, by what meanes they can, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they imagine to withſtand their deſignements? Theſe and ſuch like ſtaines we finde in Poperie, when with mature diſcuſſion we trie the ſame.</p>
            <p>For your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to our <hi>Churches,</hi> we knowe nothing in our Religion, whie anie <hi>Chriſtian</hi> maie not reſort to our <hi>Churche,</hi> without danger of ſinning; nay one the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:7293:81"/> we dare affirme, that without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Gods heavie diſpleaſure, you maie not abſent your ſelues from our <hi>Churches <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt</hi> becauſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to heare <hi>Gods word,</hi> which is there read, yourſelues cannot denie it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the Realme require it, againſt which (vnleſſe they require things vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie) al diſobedience is ſinne: and there can be noe vngodlyneſſe, in heareing Gods word, and godlie praiers. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the not comming to our <hi>Churches,</hi> is a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our comming to be not good; which is vncharitable, vnleſſe it be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon a better foundation, then anie that I heare <hi>Recuſants</hi> can lay. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Fourthly</hi> in comming, they come not to that which is evil (for that is confeſſed even of the greateſt <hi>Recuſants</hi> that I knowe) But of this before.</p>
            <p>But how falleth it out that there is here not one worde of the Claime of <hi>Antiquity</hi> of your <hi>Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> Before you ſaid that if it might be proued that you might without incurring deadlie ſinne, goe to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:7293:81"/> Church: or your <hi>Religion</hi> profeſſed now by you, not to be of ſuch <hi>Antiquity</hi> as there you claime &amp;c. Now here this Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is quite left out, as if you rued, you made that former offer. If it be becauſe you ſtand in doubt (as iuſtlie you maie) whether vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mature diſcuſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that which you now profeſſe, wilbe found to be al on with that which at the firſt was taught in this Land, repent in time, and leaue them that haue ſo long deceiued you. But wee knowing our faith to be no other, then that which was heare at the firſt taught (for the Apoſtles nether anie other who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they thought fit to inſtruct vs, would teach any other then according to that <hi>true patterne of wholſome words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1. i3</note> which was deliuered to them) thinke it great rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, that ſuch as wittinglie withſtand the <hi>Truth,</hi> or refuſe to come to that <hi>great ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> ſhould be for our parts, by ſuch <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Cenſures</hi> as we haue, compelled to come to the <hi>Goſpell of Saluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to confeſſe the truth, I ſuppoſe that we are rather to be reproued, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:7293:82"/> to cold in this worke of the Lord, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for being to ſharpo, againſt you, who ſo ſtubburnlie refuſe the offer of Saluation and abuſe the clemencie that hath beene ſhewed. But what meaneth this, that you would not we ſhould perſecute you with any <hi>ſpiritual Cenſure?</hi> Sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d you ſo much in feare of <hi>Excommunication?</hi> Theſe your words and your doings are as two ſtrings quite out of tune. Here you would not in any wiſe be <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> and yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed you wil not in anie wiſe come to our <hi>Churches.</hi> You wil not come to them your ſelus, nether would you haue vs put you out of them. But this I tel you, when anie of you come, we wil not keep you out. For your returning to god, and to his Church, is it that we deſire earneſtlie, &amp; hartelie praie for, that God will worke it in you.</p>
            <p>Now if our ſelues ſee no reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the <hi>Cenſures</hi> againſt you: leſſe cauſe is there for vs to mediate vnto his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, that ſuch da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous Subiects, as your verie <hi>Religion</hi> maketh you to be, ſhoulde
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:7293:82"/> without controlement of <hi>Law,</hi> liue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Dominion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Jt is fitter for vs to make ſuch ſuit to his Maieſty againſt you, as S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> (a man of ſingular lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and nothing giuen to crueltie,) did verie often make vnto ſuch as were Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors about him, that by puniſhments (ſo that not by death) they wold repreſſe the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> thoſe <hi>hereticks;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epi.</hi> 127. <hi>Epi.</hi> 129. <hi>Ep.</hi> 158 159</note> as in his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles</hi> to <hi>Donatus</hi> who was <hi>Proconſull in Aphrica,</hi> to <hi>Olimpius,</hi> alſo to <hi>Marcellinus</hi> a <hi>Tribune,</hi> and manie other, it maie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. So that the Cauſes that wee can thinke vpon, which maie induce vs to mooue anie thing in this matter, are as you ſee, altogither againſt your Requeſt. For indeede by that which alreadie wee haue ſeene, and by all likelyhood we may looke for at your hands, ſo virulent dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is in moſt of you, and ſo vnbrideled a courſe you thinke you ſhould run, &amp; you ſo ſnuffe if you by anie meanes bee ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, that I am verilie perſwaded, that if feare of Laws did not curb you, you wold be (if alreadie you be not) much more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulie
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:7293:83"/> then ever were the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrica.</hi> And therfore I cannot co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture, what you ſhould meane by thoſe wordes that we ſhould mediate for you, <hi>for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects beſt knowne vnto our ſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>If this iuſt and moſt equall kinde of triall ſhalbe denied vnto vs (<hi>ſaith the</hi> Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) or this our petition (like to the two former) bee ſuppreſsed without a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying anſwere; your wiſdomes cannot then but knowe it will aſſure vs, that in your owne iudgementes the cauſe of our Recuſancie, and conſtant perſevering in our Religion, are not by learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines to be diſproved, which will adde confidence in the iuſtice of our cauſe, &amp; giue notice to the world, how little vvee deſerue the opprobrious name of obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie, or other odious tearmes, dayly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vpon vs: and it maie giue cauſe that manie will thinke, that our goods or lands, and the vndoing of vs and our poſteritie, is the things more ſought, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eternall ſalvation of our ſoules. Sed meliora ſperamus.</q>
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:7293:83"/>
            <p>The <hi>Petitioner</hi> to make vs the more willing to regard his Petition, doth here inſinuate, what diſadvantage may growe vnto vs, <hi>if this iust and moſt equal kinde of trial ſhalbe denied,</hi> ſaith he. Becauſe this triall hath heretofore often already been made by writing, and yet the Petitioner ſtill vrgeth further triall: it may well bee that hee meaneth it ſhoulde bee by ſome <hi>Publike diſputation.</hi> And indeed ſome <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Thraſoes</hi> haue made as great vaunts againſt the truth, as did that prowde <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listine</hi> againſt the <hi>Hoſt of the Lord</hi> God of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and with much like ſucceſſe. As <hi>Campian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Camp. <hi>10.</hi> Rat.</note> a ſillie man for ſuch an Incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who challengeth the <hi>Vniverſities of Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> as if hee (more mightie and puiſſant then <hi>Hercules</hi>) were able to overmatch ſo manie. So did <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus</hi> too And ſo doe manie, leſſe able the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe, (though theſe are found too weake to performe their Challendge) rather in hope that it will not be granted to them, then for any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence they haue in their cauſe, if it were granted.</p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:7293:84"/>
            <p>In the beginning of her <hi>Maieſties</hi> daies before the State of <hi>Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> was ſetled, the <hi>Popiſh Biſhops</hi> &amp; others were in this tune too. And when as good order was taken to haue an <hi>Equall Triall</hi> indeed, and that indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie ſhould be vſed, for ſearching out of the Truth: though Beares may by meanes be brought to the ſtake, yet by no means would they be made to diſpute: but now by one Allegation, then by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, alwaies ſhifted of the matter. And when <hi>diſputations</hi> haue bin, <hi>Papiſts</hi> haue gained ſo little thereby, as that the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of Loraigne</hi> (no friend to <hi>Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> I trow) hauing hard <hi>Beza</hi> in the <hi>Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> at <hi>Poiſſy,</hi> in the preſence of the <hi>French King</hi> and al the <hi>Great Peeres</hi> there aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,<note place="margin">An. hiſt. Col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lect of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Chart. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> was hard to ſaie, <hi>I woulde either this man had beene dumbe, or wee had beene all deafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what reaſon is there why this now ſhould be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted a <hi>iuſt &amp; moſt equal kind of Triall,</hi> which was by <hi>Clement the</hi> 7. (when the <hi>Emperour Charles</hi> the 5. and <hi>Frauncis the first French king,</hi> required a
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:7293:84"/> 
               <hi>free Generall Councell</hi> for deciding the queſtions in <hi>Religion</hi>) called,<note place="margin">Gentiles. e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an. Concil. Trid. li. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>res periculo ſa pravi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> exempli: a dangerous matter and of evill example?</hi> Jt is no more <hi>iuſt</hi> &amp; <hi>equall,</hi> now to call into queſtion a ſettled &amp; well grounded <hi>Religion</hi> in any <hi>State:</hi> then it was, to bring the <hi>Popiſh doctrines,</hi> which are builte of no ſure foundation to a due triall: no, nor ſo <hi>iuſt</hi> by farre.</p>
            <p>And what further triall would our <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner</hi> require of the things hee propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth? He would haue it proued to their <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> that without danger of <hi>deadly ſinne</hi> they maie reſorte to the Exerciſes of our <hi>Religion.</hi> I haue before ſhewed that this is made ſo cleare to the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> &amp; <hi>Priests</hi> too, who are the <hi>learnedſt Divines</hi> that they haue, by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bell,</hi> that they are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that it is lawfull, ſo that it bee not a <hi>ſigne diſtinctiue,</hi> as they ſuppoſe it is, but indeede it is not; for ſince manie <hi>Papiſtes</hi> come to the <hi>Church,</hi> &amp; are called <hi>Church-Papiſts</hi> and ſo we reckon of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they are as dangerous as they that come not: and likewiſe manie honeſter then any <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:7293:85"/> come not to our <hi>Churches,</hi> moued vpon an vndiſcreet zeale. Jf then neither Papiſts only abſtaine from our Churches neither yet al they, it cannot be a <hi>ſigne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctiue,</hi> &amp; ſo no hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Church.</p>
            <p>Moreover, for proofe of <hi>Popiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> that it hath not beene from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the <hi>Converſion</hi> of this land fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Gentiliſme,</hi> it is ſtrongly proued by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſundrie <hi>Arch-Papiſtes</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge almoſt all that they teach to be taken from Tradition &amp; not out of the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> and ſundrie of thoſe <hi>Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> as I haue ſhewed, are of ſo late time, that he muſt needs ſhew himſelfe verie parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that can once imagine they haue ſuch Antiquitie. So I truſt his former dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds are ſufficiently anſwered, with that which formerly hath bin alleadged, which (were it not for prolixitie) I could demonſtrate in the particular practiſe of our own cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, as in eſpeciall maie appeare in the point of the Sacrament (for which they chieflie except againſt our Service) the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:7293:85"/> verie ſame doctrine which wee now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,<note place="margin">Homil. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript. in the Libra. of Oxford Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter VVorceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Lincoln. Beda Hiſt. Eccle. Petr. Cluniac. in ep. ad. Bern.</note> being generallie retained in this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the Saxons time, with expreſſe reiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all faigned Tranſubſtantiation, as plainely maie appeare by their Homilies yet extant in the Saxons tongue. As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I could haue ſhewed by the Rites of the Eaſterne Churches, which both Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans &amp; Saxons many hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred of yeers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this Iſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was not by any of the Roman Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Now what hee meaneth by a <hi>ſatiſfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anſwere</hi> to this Petition it maie bee a queſtion. For ſome other of their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, require either <hi>Toleration of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> for exerciſe thereof, or at the leaſt, <hi>Immunitie</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> puniſhment, if they come not to our <hi>Churches.</hi> But a <hi>Chriſtian King</hi> borne and brought vp in the Light of the <hi>Truth,</hi> &amp; beautified with the ornaments of true learning; who acknowledgeth <hi>Gods</hi> vnſpeakeable goodnes towards him ſelfe, in aduancing him to ſo great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, preſeruing him from ſo manie perils, crowning him with ſo manie bleſſings;
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:7293:86"/> whoſe <hi>Religion</hi> teacheth him to pray to <hi>God only,</hi> by the <hi>Mediation</hi> of <hi>Chriſt alone</hi> and to offer vnto him for his graces, the <hi>Calues</hi> of his lips, praiſe &amp; thankſgiuing: ſuch a <hi>king</hi> (I ſaie) ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ignorant, that to tolerate, a <hi>Sect</hi> of People in his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, that ſhould cal vpon <hi>Saints</hi> &amp; <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> and ſo darken <hi>Gods</hi> honor, prophane his Name, &amp; deſpiſe his Word, may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke againſt <hi>him,</hi> &amp; <hi>his,</hi> the heauie Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of him, who being king of kings, doth require of them this Royal ſeruice of preſeruing inviolable the ſinceritie of his <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> in their kingdomes.</p>
            <p>And looke how manie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts there are to roote out <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> deſtroie <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters,</hi> aboliſh their <hi>groues,</hi> their <hi>Altars</hi> to ſhunne <hi>converſing</hi> or <hi>marrying</hi> with them; how many threatnings againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that performe not theſe offices; how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples of the Godlie, commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for doing them: ſo many Arguments there are againſt, not onlie Toleration but euen connive<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie a ſuch ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:7293:86"/>
            <p>And therfore to ſatiſfy them, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you tearme your <hi>Learned Diuines</hi> we thinke it a thing moſt eaſie, in reſpect of the cauſe, yet moſt impoſſible in reſpect of the perſons. For it ſtandeth them vpon <hi>not to be ſatiſfied,</hi> eſpecially they being, ſuch as rather reſpect their owne mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, then your ſaluation, whatſoeuer they prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. If they ſhould confeſſe, that our Reaſons <hi>ſatiſfie</hi> them, and you ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon reſort to our Churches, your liking of them will ſoone decay, and their ſtate muſt needs be much impaired, which by their good wils I warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you ſhal neuer be</p>
            <p>But if anie <hi>Recuſant</hi> being deſirous to know the Truth, repaire to our <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or other in our Church of <hi>ſingular note</hi> of Learning (as you ſpeake) for reſolution of anie point in controuerſie between vs and your <hi>Diuines;</hi> if ſufficient reaſons be not yeelded out of Gods booke, and the purer <hi>Fathers,</hi> of that doctrine we profeſſe, and againſt that that you hold, euen ſuch as your <hi>Learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines</hi> ſhal not be able to anſwere them
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:7293:87"/> then I confeſſe, you haue iuſt cauſe to ſpeake of the goodnes of your cauſe, &amp; to alleadge your perſeuering therein. But your cauſe being of it ſelfe not good, as we ſhall alwaies by Gods grace, be readie to iuſtifie: you haue no more cauſe to brag of your ſufferings &amp; conſtancy, nor ſo much neither, as had the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> at whoſe wilfull yea and deſired deaths, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Aug. in. epiſt.</note> marueileth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scriptures</hi> therefore, and conſent of <hi>Antiquity</hi> being as in part I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed in this ſhort Anſwer, ſo plaine with vs as they are, neither can you in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Recuſants,</hi> avoide the note of <hi>obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie:</hi> or others once deeme, that ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt a <hi>Religion</hi> as the <hi>Romiſh</hi> is, cannot ſufficiently by godly and Chriſtian lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, bee diſproued. As for that you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that (vnleſſe your <hi>Requests</hi> be gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) cauſe wilbe giuen to many to thinke your lands and goods are ſought for, and the vndoing of you and your poſteritie, rather then your ſalvation, it maie wel be that ſuch vndutifull ſurmiſes are often in
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:7293:87"/> your harts, and ſuch malitious reports in your mouthes. But is there ſo much as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny colour why any ſhould ſo thinke?</p>
            <p>Leauing therfore the iuſter examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this vniuſt charge, to trie whether wee ſeeke their goods and vndoing or not, to him who knoweth the ſecrets of all harts, and ſhal one daie reveale &amp; reward ſuch vncharitable ſurmiſes: we wiſh vnto the <hi>Petitioner</hi> and al <hi>Recuſants,</hi> that it would pleaſe God to indue them with better grace, that ſeeing the Errours wherinto they are lead, and rightly conſidering of the blind devotions, wherwith they are delighted, they maie deteſt ſuch abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and forſaking both the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Poperie</hi> cleaue ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlie and ſincerlie both to our God and to our Soveraigne, that they &amp; we with one voice and hart, maie ſinge the ſonges of <hi>Sion</hi> to the Lorde our God. This is the onlie waie to hope for better things here, &amp; to obtaine the beſt thinges elſewhere.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
